<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><sura id="5">  <aya id="1" text="O you who believe! Fulfill (your) obligations. Lawful to you (for food) are all the beasts of cattle except that which will be announced to you (herein), game (also) being unlawful when you assume &lt;I&gt;Ihrâm &lt;/I&gt;for &lt;I&gt;Hajj &lt;/I&gt;or '&lt;I&gt;Umrah &lt;/I&gt;(pilgrimage). Verily, Allâh commands that which He wills." />  <aya id="2" text="O you who believe! Violate not the sanctity of the Symbols of Allâh, nor of the Sacred Month, nor of the animals brought for sacrifice, nor the garlanded people or animals, etc. [Marked by the garlands on their necks made from the outer part of the tree&amp;#173;stems (of Makkah) for their security], nor the people coming to the Sacred House (Makkah), seeking the bounty and good pleasure of their Lord. But when you finish the &lt;I&gt;Ihrâm &lt;/I&gt;(of &lt;I&gt;Hajj &lt;/I&gt;or '&lt;I&gt;Umrah&lt;/I&gt;), you may hunt, and let not the hatred of some people in (once) stopping you from &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Masjid&amp;#173;al&amp;#173;Harâm &lt;/I&gt;(at Makkah) lead you to transgression (and hostility on your part). Help you one another in &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Birr &lt;/I&gt;and &lt;I&gt;At&amp;#173;Taqwa &lt;/I&gt;(virtue, righteousness and piety); but do not help one another in sin and transgression. And fear Allâh. Verily, Allâh is Severe in punishment." />  <aya id="3" text="Forbidden to you (for food) are: &lt;I&gt;Al-Maytatah &lt;/I&gt;(the dead animals - cattle-beast not slaughtered), blood, the flesh of swine, and the meat of that which has been slaughtered as a sacrifice for others than Allâh, or has been slaughtered for idols, etc., or on which Allâh's Name has not been mentioned while slaughtering, and that which has been killed by strangling, or by a violent blow, or by a headlong fall, or by the goring of horns - and that which has been (partly) eaten by a wild animal - unless you are able to slaughter it (before its death) &amp;#173; and that which is sacrificed (slaughtered) on &lt;I&gt;An&amp;#173;Nusub&lt;/I&gt; (stone altars). (Forbidden) also is to use arrows seeking luck or decision, (all) that is &lt;I&gt;Fisqun &lt;/I&gt;(disobedience of Allâh and sin). This day, those who disbelieved have given up all hope of your religion, so fear them not, but fear Me. This day, I have perfected your religion for you, completed My Favour upon you, and have chosen for you Islâm as your religion. But as for him who is forced by severe hunger, with no inclination to sin (such can eat these above-mentioned meats), then surely, Allâh is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="4" text="They ask you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) what is lawful for them (as food ). Say: &amp;quot;Lawful unto you are &lt;I&gt;At&amp;#173;Tayyibât &lt;/I&gt;[all kind of &lt;I&gt;Halâl &lt;/I&gt;(lawful&amp;#173;good) foods which Allâh has made lawful (meat of slaughtered eatable animals, milk products, fats, vegetables and fruits, etc.)]. And those beasts and birds of prey which you have trained as hounds, training and teaching them (to catch) in the manner as directed to you by Allâh; so eat of what they catch for you, but pronounce the Name of Allâh over it, and fear Allâh. Verily, Allâh is Swift in reckoning.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="5" text="Made lawful to you this day are &lt;I&gt;At&amp;#173;Tayyibât &lt;/I&gt;[all kinds of &lt;I&gt;Halâl &lt;/I&gt;(lawful) foods, which Allâh has made lawful (meat of slaughtered eatable animals, etc., milk products, fats, vegetables and fruits, etc.). The food (slaughtered cattle, eatable animals, etc.) of the people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians) is lawful to you and yours is lawful to them. (Lawful to you in marriage) are chaste women from the believers and chaste women from those who were given the Scripture (Jews and Christians) before your time, when you have given their due &lt;I&gt;Mahr &lt;/I&gt;(bridal money given by the husband to his wife at the time of marriage), desiring chastity (i.e. taking them in legal wedlock) not committing illegal sexual intercourse, nor taking them as girl-friends. And whosoever disbelieves in the Oneness of Allâh and in all the other Articles of Faith [i.e. His (Allâh's), Angels, His Holy Books, His Messengers, the Day of Resurrection and &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Qadar &lt;/I&gt;(Divine Preordainments)], then fruitless is his work, and in the Hereafter he will be among the losers." />  <aya id="6" text="O you who believe! When you intend to offer &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (the prayer), wash your faces and your hands (forearms) up to the elbows, rub (by passing wet hands over) your heads, and (wash) your feet up to ankles . If you are in a state of &lt;I&gt;Janâba &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. had a sexual discharge), purify yourself (bathe your whole body). But if you are ill or on a journey or any of you comes from answering the call of nature, or you have been in contact with women (i.e. sexual intercourse) and you find no water, then perform &lt;I&gt;Tayammum&lt;/I&gt; with clean earth and rub therewith your faces and hands. Allâh does not want to place you in difficulty, but He wants to purify you, and to complete His Favour on you that you may be thankful." />  <aya id="7" text="And remember Allâh's Favour upon you and His Covenant with which He bound you when you said: &amp;quot;We hear and we obey.&amp;quot; And fear Allâh. Verily, Allâh is All&amp;#173;Knower of the secrets of (your) breasts." />  <aya id="8" text="O you who believe! Stand out firmly for Allâh and be just witnesses and let not the enmity and hatred of others make you avoid justice. Be just: that is nearer to piety, and fear Allâh. Verily, Allâh is Well&amp;#173;Acquainted with what you do." />  <aya id="9" text="Allâh has promised those who believe (in the Oneness of Allâh - Islâmic Monotheism) and do deeds of righteousness, that for them there is forgiveness and a great reward (i.e. Paradise)." />  <aya id="10" text="They who disbelieve and deny our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) are those who will be the dwellers of the Hell&amp;#173;fire." />  <aya id="11" text="O you who believe! Remember the Favour of Allâh unto you when some people desired (made a plan) to stretch out their hands against you, but (Allâh) withheld their hands from you. So fear Allâh. And in Allâh let believers put their trust." />  <aya id="12" text="Indeed Allâh took the covenant from the Children of Israel (Jews), and We appointed twelve leaders among them. And Allâh said: &amp;quot;I am with you if you perform &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (&lt;I&gt;Iqâmat-as-Salât&lt;/I&gt;) and give &lt;I&gt;Zakât &lt;/I&gt;and believe in My Messengers; honour and assist them, and lend to Allâh a good loan. Verily, I will remit your sins and admit you to Gardens under which rivers flow (in Paradise). But if any of you after this, disbelieved, he has indeed gone astray from the Straight Path.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="13" text="So because of their breach of their covenant, We cursed them, and made their hearts grow hard. They change the words from their (right) places and have abandoned a good part of the Message that was sent to them. And you will not cease to discover deceit in them, except a few of them. But forgive them, and overlook (their misdeeds). Verily, Allâh loves &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Muhsinûn &lt;/I&gt;(good&amp;#173;doers - see V.2:112)." />  <aya id="14" text="And from those who call themselves Christians, We took their covenant, but they have abandoned a good part of the Message that was sent to them. So We planted amongst them enmity and hatred till the Day of Resurrection (when they discarded Allâh's Book, disobeyed Allâh's Messengers and His Orders and transgressed beyond bounds in Allâh's disobedience), and Allâh will inform them of what they used to do." />  <aya id="15" text="O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Now has come to you Our Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) explaining to you much of that which you used to hide from the Scripture and passing over (i.e. leaving out without explaining) much. Indeed, there has come to you from Allâh a light (Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; ) and a plain Book (this Qur'ân)." />  <aya id="16" text="Wherewith Allâh guides all those who seek His Good Pleasure to ways of peace, and He brings them out of darkness by His Will unto light and guides them to a Straight Way (Islâmic Monotheism)." />  <aya id="17" text="Surely, in disbelief are they who say that Allâh is the Messiah, son of Maryam (Mary) . Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Who then has the least power against Allâh, if He were to destroy the Messiah, son of Maryam (Mary), his mother, and all those who are on the earth together?&amp;quot; And to Allâh belongs the dominion of the heavens and the earth, and all that is between them. He creates what He wills. And Allâh is Able to do all things." />  <aya id="18" text="And (both) the Jews and the Christians say: &amp;quot;We are the children of Allâh and His loved ones.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Why then does He punish you for your sins?&amp;quot; Nay, you are but human beings, of those He has created, He forgives whom He wills and He punishes whom He wills. And to Allâh belongs the dominion of the heavens and the earth and all that is between them, and to Him is the return (of all)." />  <aya id="19" text="O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Now has come to you Our Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) making (things) clear unto you, after a break in (the series of) Messengers, lest you say: &amp;quot;There came unto us no bringer of glad tidings and no warner. &amp;quot; But now has come unto you a bringer of glad tidings and a warner. And Allâh is Able to do all things." />  <aya id="20" text="And (remember) when Mûsa (Moses) said to his people: &amp;quot;O my people! Remember the Favour of Allâh to you, when He made Prophets among you, made you kings, and gave you what He had not given to any other among the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind and jinns, in the past).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="21" text="&amp;quot;O my people! Enter the holy land (Palestine) which Allâh has assigned to you, and turn not back (in flight) for then you will be returned as losers.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="22" text="They said: &amp;quot;O Mûsa (Moses)! In it (this holy land) are a people of great strength, and we shall never enter it, till they leave it; when they leave, then we will enter.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="23" text="Two men of those who feared (Allâh and) on whom Allâh had bestowed His Grace [they were íæÔÚ æ ßÇáÈ Yûsha' (Joshua) and Kâlab (Caleb)] said: &amp;quot;Assault them through the gate, for when you are in, victory will be yours, and put your trust in Allâh if you are believers indeed.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="24" text="They said: &amp;quot;O Mûsa (Moses)! We shall never enter it as long as they are there. So go you and your Lord and fight you two, we are sitting right here.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="25" text="He [Mûsa (Moses)] said: &amp;quot;O my Lord! I have power only over myself and my brother, so separate us from the people who are the &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious and disobedient to Allâh)!&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="26" text="(Allâh) said: &amp;quot;Therefore it (this holy land) is forbidden to them for forty years; in distraction they will wander through the land. So be not sorrowful over the people who are the &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious and disobedient to Allâh).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="27" text="And (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) recite to them (the Jews) the story of the two sons of Adam [Hâbil (Abel) and Qâbil (Cain)] in truth; when each offered a sacrifice (to Allâh), it was accepted from the one but not from the other. The latter said to the former: &amp;quot;I will surely kill you. &amp;quot; The former said: &amp;quot;Verily, Allâh accepts only from those who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="28" text="&amp;quot;If you do stretch your hand against me to kill me, I shall never stretch my hand against you to kill you, for I fear Allâh; the Lord of the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind, jinns, and all that exists).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="29" text="&amp;quot;Verily, I intend to let you draw my sin on yourself as well as yours, then you will be one of the dwellers of the Fire, and that is the recompense of the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="30" text="So the &lt;I&gt;Nafs&lt;/I&gt; (self) of the other (latter one) encouraged him and made fair&amp;#173;seeming to him the murder of his brother; he murdered him and became one of the losers." />  <aya id="31" text="Then Allâh sent a crow who scratched the ground to show him to hide the dead body of his brother. He (the murderer) said: &amp;quot;Woe to me! Am I not even able to be as this crow and to hide the dead body of my brother?&amp;quot; Then he became one of those who regretted." />  <aya id="32" text="Because of that We ordained for the Children of Israel that if anyone killed a person not in retaliation of murder, or (and) to spread mischief in the land - it would be as if he killed all mankind, and if anyone saved a life, it would be as if he saved the life of all mankind. And indeed, there came to them Our Messengers with clear proofs, evidences, and signs, even then after that many of them continued to exceed the limits (e.g. by doing oppression unjustly and exceeding beyond the limits set by Allâh by committing the major sins) in the land!." />  <aya id="33" text="The recompense of those who wage war against Allâh and His Messenger and do mischief in the land is only that they shall be killed or crucified or their hands and their feet be cut off on the opposite sides, or be exiled from the land. That is their disgrace in this world, and a great torment is theirs in the Hereafter." />  <aya id="34" text="Except for those who (having fled away and then) came back (as Muslims) with repentance before they fall into your power; in that case, know that Allâh is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="35" text="O you who believe! Do your duty to Allâh and fear Him. Seek the means of approach to Him, and strive hard in His Cause as much as you can. So that you may be successful." />  <aya id="36" text="Verily, those who disbelieve, if they had all that is in the earth, and as much again therewith to ransom themselves thereby from the torment on the Day of Resurrection, it would never be accepted of them, and theirs would be a painful torment." />  <aya id="37" text="They will long to get out of the Fire, but never will they get out therefrom, and theirs will be a lasting torment." />  <aya id="38" text="Cut off (from the wrist joint) the (right) hand of the thief, male or female, as a recompense for that which they committed, a punishment by way of example from Allâh. And Allâh is All&amp;#173;Powerful, All&amp;#173;Wise." />  <aya id="39" text="But whosoever repents after his crime and does righteous good deeds (by obeying Allâh), then verily, Allâh will pardon him (accept his repentance). Verily, Allâh is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="40" text="Know you not that to Allâh (Alone) belongs the dominion of the heavens and the earth! He punishes whom He wills and He forgives whom He wills. And Allâh is Able to do all things." />  <aya id="41" text="O Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)! Let not those who hurry to fall into disbelief grieve you, of such who say: &amp;quot;We believe&amp;quot; with their mouths but their hearts have no faith. And of the Jews are men who listen much and eagerly to lies - listen to others who have not come to you. They change the words from their places; they say, &amp;quot;If you are given this, take it, but if you are not given this, then beware!&amp;quot; And whomsoever Allâh wants to put in &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Fitnah &lt;/I&gt;[error, because of his rejecting the Faith], you can do nothing for him against Allâh. Those are the ones whose hearts Allâh does not want to purify (from disbelief and hypocrisy); for them there is a disgrace in this world, and in the Hereafter a great torment." />  <aya id="42" text="(They like to) listen to falsehood, to devour anything forbidden. So if they come to you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), either judge between them, or turn away from them. If you turn away from them, they cannot hurt you in the least. And if you judge, judge with justice between them. Verily, Allâh loves those who act justly." />  <aya id="43" text="But how do they come to you for decision while they have the Taurât (Torah), in which is the (plain) Decision of Allâh; yet even after that, they turn away. For they are not (really) believers." />  <aya id="44" text="Verily, We did send down the Taurât (Torah) [to Mûsa (Moses)], therein was guidance and light, by which the Prophets, who submitted themselves to Allâh's Will, judged the Jews. And the rabbis and the priests [too judged the Jews by the Taurât (Torah) after those Prophets] for to them was entrusted the protection of Allâh's Book, and they were witnesses thereto. Therefore fear not men but fear Me (O Jews) and sell not My Verses for a miserable price. And whosoever does not judge by what Allâh has revealed, such are the &lt;I&gt;Kâfirûn &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. disbelievers - of a lesser degree as they do not act on Allâh's Laws )." />  <aya id="45" text="And We ordained therein for them: &amp;quot;Life for life , eye for eye, nose for nose, ear for ear, tooth for tooth, and wounds equal for equal.&amp;quot; But if anyone remits the retaliation by way of charity, it shall be for him an expiation. And whosoever does not judge by that which Allâh has revealed, such are the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers - of a lesser degree)." />  <aya id="46" text="And in their footsteps, We sent 'Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary) , confirming the Taurât (Torah) that had come before him, and We gave him the Injeel (Gospel), in which was guidance and light and confirmation of the Taurât (Torah) that had come before it, a guidance and an admonition for &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="47" text="Let the people of the Injeel (Gospel) judge by what Allâh has revealed therein. And whosoever does not judge by what Allâh has revealed (then) such (people) are the &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the rebellious i.e. disobedient (of a lesser degree) to Allâh." />  <aya id="48" text="And We have sent down to you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) the Book (this Qur'ân) in truth, confirming the Scripture that came before it and &lt;I&gt;Mohayminan &lt;/I&gt;(trustworthy in highness and a witness) over it (old Scriptures) . So judge between them by what Allâh has revealed, and follow not their vain desires, diverging away from the truth that has come to you. To each among you, We have prescribed a law and a clear way. If Allâh willed, He would have made you one nation, but that (He) may test you in what He has given you; so strive as in a race in good deeds. The return of you (all) is to Allâh; then He will inform you about that in which you used to differ." />  <aya id="49" text=". And so judge (you O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) between them by what Allâh has revealed and follow not their vain desires, but beware of them lest they turn you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) far away from some of that which Allâh has sent down to you. And if they turn away, then know that Allâh's Will is to punish them for some sins of theirs. And truly, most of men are &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious and disobedient to Allâh)." />  <aya id="50" text="Do they then seek the judgement of (the Days of) Ignorance? And who is better in judgement than Allâh for a people who have firm Faith." />  <aya id="51" text="O you who believe! Take not the Jews and the Christians as &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;(friends, protectors, helpers, etc.), they are but &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;to one another. And if any amongst you takes them as &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ', &lt;/I&gt;then surely he is one of them. Verily, Allâh guides not those people who are the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers and unjust)." />  <aya id="52" text="And you see those in whose hearts there is a disease (of hypocrisy), they hurry to their friendship, saying: &amp;quot;We fear lest some misfortune of a disaster may befall us.&amp;quot; Perhaps Allâh may bring a victory or a decision according to His Will. Then they will become regretful for what they have been keeping as a secret in themselves." />  <aya id="53" text="And those who believe will say: &amp;quot;Are these the men (hypocrites) who swore their strongest oaths by Allâh that they were with you (Muslims)?&amp;quot; All that they did has been in vain (because of their hypocrisy), and they have become the losers." />  <aya id="54" text="O you who believe! Whoever from among you turns back from his religion (Islâm), Allâh will bring a people whom He will love and they will love Him; humble towards the believers, stern towards the disbelievers, fighting in the Way of Allâh, and never afraid of the blame of the blamers. That is the Grace of Allâh which He bestows on whom He wills. And Allâh is All&amp;#173;Sufficient for His creatures' needs, All&amp;#173;Knower." />  <aya id="55" text="Verily, your &lt;I&gt;Walî &lt;/I&gt;(Protector or Helper) is Allâh, His Messenger, and the believers, - those who perform &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (&lt;I&gt;Iqâmat-as-Salât&lt;/I&gt;), and give &lt;I&gt;Zakât&lt;/I&gt;, and they bow down (submit themselves with obedience to Allâh in prayer)." />  <aya id="56" text="And whosoever takes Allâh, His Messenger, and those who have believed, as Protectors, then the party of Allâh will be the victorious." />  <aya id="57" text="O you who believe! Take not for &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;(protectors and helpers) those who take your religion for a mockery and fun from among those who received the Scripture (Jews and Christians) before you, nor from among the disbelievers; and fear Allâh if you indeed are true believers." />  <aya id="58" text="And when you proclaim the call for &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; [call for the prayer (&lt;I&gt;Adhân&lt;/I&gt;)], they take it (but) as a mockery and fun; that is because they are a people who understand not." />  <aya id="59" text="Say: &amp;quot;O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Do you criticize us for no other reason than that we believe in Allâh, and in (the revelation) which has been sent down to us and in that which has been sent down before (us), and that most of you are &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;[rebellious and disobedient (to Allâh)]?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="60" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; to the people of the Scripture): &amp;quot;Shall I inform you of something worse than that, regarding the recompense from Allâh: those (Jews) who incurred the Curse of Allâh and His Wrath, those of whom (some) He transformed into monkeys and swines, those who worshipped &lt;I&gt;Tâghût&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;(false deities); such are worse in rank (on the Day of Resurrection in the Hell&amp;#173;fire), and far more astray from the Right Path (in the life of this world).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="61" text="When they come to you, they say: &amp;quot;We believe.&amp;quot; But in fact they enter with (an intention of) disbelief and they go out with the same. And Allâh knows all what they were hiding." />  <aya id="62" text="And you see many of them (Jews) hurrying for sin and transgression, and eating illegal things [as bribes and &lt;I&gt;Ribâ &lt;/I&gt;(usury), etc.]. Evil indeed is that which they have been doing." />  <aya id="63" text="Why do not the rabbis and the religious learned men forbid them from uttering sinful words and from eating illegal things. Evil indeed is that which they have been performing." />  <aya id="64" text="The Jews say: &amp;quot;Allâh's Hand is tied up (i.e. He does not give and spend of His Bounty).&amp;quot; Be their hands tied up and be they accursed for what they uttered. Nay, both His Hands are widely outstretched. He spends (of His Bounty) as He wills. Verily, the Revelation that has come to you from Allâh increases in most of them their obstinate rebellion and disbelief. We have put enmity and hatred amongst them till the Day of Resurrection. Every time they kindled the fire of war, Allâh extinguished it; and they (ever) strive to make mischief on earth. And Allâh does not like the &lt;I&gt;Mufsidûn &lt;/I&gt;(mischief&amp;#173;makers)." />  <aya id="65" text="And if only the people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians) had believed (in Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and warded off evil (sin, ascribing partners to Allâh) and had become &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Muttaqûn&lt;/I&gt; (the pious - see V.2:2) We would indeed have blotted out their sins and admitted them to Gardens of pleasure (in Paradise)." />  <aya id="66" text="And if only they had acted according to the Taurât (Torah), the Injeel (Gospel), and what has (now) been sent down to them from their Lord (the Qur'ân), they would surely have gotten provision from above them and from underneath their feet. There are from among them people who are on the right course (i.e. they act on the revelation and believe in Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; like 'Abdullâh bin Salâm ÑÖì &lt;&lt;code2&gt;&gt; &lt;&lt;codeb&gt;&gt;), but many of them do evil deeds." />  <aya id="67" text="O Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)! Proclaim (the Message) which has been sent down to you from your Lord. And if you do not, then you have not conveyed His Message. Allâh will protect you from mankind. Verily, Allâh guides not the people who disbelieve." />  <aya id="68" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) &amp;quot;O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! You have nothing (as regards guidance) till you act according to the Taurât (Torah), the Injeel (Gospel), and what has (now) been sent down to you from your Lord (the Qur'ân).&amp;quot; Verily, that which has been sent down to you (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) from your Lord increases in many of them their obstinate rebellion and disbelief. So be not sorrowful over the people who disbelieve." />  <aya id="69" text="Surely, those who believe (in the Oneness of Allâh, in His Messenger Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; and all that was revealed to him from Allâh), those who are the Jews and the Sabians and the Christians, - whosoever believed in Allâh and the Last Day, and worked righteousness, on them shall be no fear, nor shall they grieve." />  <aya id="70" text="Verily, We took the covenant of the Children of Israel and sent them Messengers. Whenever there came to them a Messenger with what they themselves desired not - a group of them they called liars, and others among them they killed." />  <aya id="71" text="They thought there will be no &lt;I&gt;Fitnah &lt;/I&gt;(trial or punishment), so they became blind and deaf; after that Allâh turned to them (with Forgiveness); yet again many of them became blind and deaf. And Allâh is the All&amp;#173;Seer of what they do." />  <aya id="72" text="Surely, they have disbelieved who say: &amp;quot;Allâh is the Messiah ['Iesa (Jesus)], son of Maryam (Mary).&amp;quot; But the Messiah ['Iesa (Jesus)] said: &amp;quot;O Children of Israel! Worship Allâh, my Lord and your Lord.&amp;quot; Verily, whosoever sets up partners in worship with Allâh, then Allâh has forbidden Paradise for him, and the Fire will be his abode . And for the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers) there are no helpers." />  <aya id="73" text="Surely, disbelievers are those who said: &amp;quot;Allâh is the third of the three (in a Trinity).&amp;quot; But there is no &lt;I&gt;ilâh &lt;/I&gt;(god) (none who has the right to be worshipped) but One &lt;I&gt;Ilâh &lt;/I&gt;(God -Allâh). And if they cease not from what they say, verily, a painful torment will befall the disbelievers among them." />  <aya id="74" text="Will they not repent to Allâh and ask His Forgiveness? For Allâh is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="75" text="The Messiah ['Iesa (Jesus)], son of Maryam (Mary), was no more than a Messenger; many were the Messengers that passed away before him. His mother [Maryam (Mary)] was a &lt;I&gt;Siddiqah &lt;/I&gt;[i.e. she believed in the words of Allâh and His Books (see Verse 66:12)]. They both used to eat food (as any other human being, while Allâh does not eat). Look how We make the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) clear to them, yet look how they are deluded away (from the truth)." />  <aya id="76" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; to mankind): &amp;quot;How do you worship besides Allâh something which has no power either to harm or to benefit you? But it is Allâh Who is the All&amp;#173;Hearer, All&amp;#173;Knower.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="77" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Exceed not the limits in your religion (by believing in something) other than the truth, and do not follow the vain desires of people who went astray in times gone by, and who misled many, and strayed (themselves) from the Right Path.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="78" text="Those among the Children of Israel who disbelieved were cursed by the tongue of Dawûd (David) and 'Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary). That was because they disobeyed (Allâh and the Messengers) and were ever transgressing beyond bounds." />  <aya id="79" text="They used not to forbid one another from the &lt;I&gt;Munkar &lt;/I&gt;(wrong, evil&amp;#173;doing, sins, polytheism, disbelief, etc.) which they committed. Vile indeed was what they used to do." />  <aya id="80" text="You see many of them taking the disbelievers as their &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;(protectors and helpers). Evil indeed is that which their ownselves have sent forward before them, for that (reason) Allâh's Wrath fell upon them and in torment they will abide." />  <aya id="81" text="And had they believed in Allâh, and in the Prophet (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and in what has been revealed to him, never would they have taken them (the disbelievers) as &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;(protectors and helpers), but many of them are the &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious, disobedient to Allâh)." />  <aya id="82" text="Verily, you will find the strongest among men in enmity to the believers (Muslims) the Jews and those who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(see V.2:105), and you will find the nearest in love to the believers (Muslims) those who say: &amp;quot;We are Christians.&amp;quot; That is because amongst them are priests and monks, and they are not proud." />  <aya id="83" text="And when they (who call themselves Christians) listen to what has been sent down to the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), you see their eyes overflowing with tears because of the truth they have recognised. They say: &amp;quot;Our Lord! We believe; so write us down among the witnesses." />  <aya id="84" text="&amp;quot;And why should we not believe in Allâh and in that which has come to us of the truth (Islâmic Monotheism)? And we wish that our Lord will admit us (in Paradise on the Day of Resurrection) along with the righteous people (Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; and his Companions ÑÖì &lt;&lt;code2&gt;&gt; &lt;&lt;codeb&gt;&gt;ã).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="85" text="So because of what they said, Allâh rewarded them Gardens under which rivers flow (in Paradise), they will abide therein forever. Such is the reward of good&amp;#173;doers." />  <aya id="86" text="But those who disbelieved and belied Our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.), they shall be the dwellers of the (Hell) Fire." />  <aya id="87" text="O you who believe! Make not unlawful the &lt;I&gt;Taiyibât &lt;/I&gt;(all that is good as regards foods, things, deeds, beliefs, persons, etc.) which Allâh has made lawful to you, and transgress not. Verily, Allâh does not like the transgressors." />  <aya id="88" text="And eat of the things which Allâh has provided for you, lawful and good, and fear Allâh in Whom you believe." />  <aya id="89" text="Allâh will not punish you for what is uninentional in your oaths, but He will punish you for your deliberate oaths; for its expiation (a deliberate oath) feed ten &lt;I&gt;Masâkin&lt;/I&gt; (poor persons), on a scale of the average of that with which you feed your own families; or clothe them; or manumit a slave. But whosoever cannot afford (that), then he should fast for three days. That is the expiation for the oaths when you have sworn . And protect your oaths (i.e. do not swear much) . Thus Allâh make clear to you His &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) that you may be grateful." />  <aya id="90" text="O you who believe! Intoxicants (all kinds of alcoholic drinks), gambling, &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Ansâb&lt;/I&gt; , and &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Azlâm &lt;/I&gt;(arrows for seeking luck or decision) are an abomination of &lt;I&gt;Shaitân&lt;/I&gt;'s (Satan) handiwork. So avoid (strictly all) that (abomination) in order that you may be successful ." />  <aya id="91" text="&lt;I&gt;Shaitân&lt;/I&gt; (Satan) wants only to excite enmity and hatred between you with intoxicants (alcoholic drinks) and gambling, and hinder you from the remembrance of Allâh and from &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (the prayer). So, will you not then abstain?" />  <aya id="92" text="And obey Allâh and the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), and beware (of even coming near to drinking or gambling or &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Ansâb, &lt;/I&gt;or &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Azlâm&lt;/I&gt;, etc.) and fear Allâh. Then if you turn away, you should know that it is Our Messenger's duty to convey (the Message) in the clearest way." />  <aya id="93" text="Those who believe and do righteous good deeds, there is no sin on them for what they ate (in the past), if they fear Allâh (by keeping away from His forbidden things), and believe and do righteous good deeds, and again fear Allâh and believe, and once again fear Allâh and do good deeds with &lt;I&gt;Ihsân &lt;/I&gt;(perfection). And Allâh loves the good&amp;#173;doers." />  <aya id="94" text="O you who believe! Allâh will certainly make a trial of you with something in (the matter of) the game that is well within reach of your hands and your lances, that Allâh may test who fears Him unseen. Then whoever transgresses thereafter, for him there is a painful torment." />  <aya id="95" text="O you who believe! Kill not game while you are in a state of &lt;I&gt;Ihrâm &lt;/I&gt;for &lt;I&gt;Hajj &lt;/I&gt;or '&lt;I&gt;Umrah &lt;/I&gt;(pilgrimage), and whosoever of you kills it intentionally, the penalty is an offering, brought to the Ka'bah, of an eatable animal (i.e. sheep, goat, cow, etc.) equivalent to the one he killed, as adjudged by two just men among you; or, for expiation, he should feed &lt;I&gt;Masâkin &lt;/I&gt;(poor persons), or its equivalent in &lt;I&gt;Saum&lt;/I&gt; (fasting), that he may taste the heaviness (punishment) of his deed. Allâh has forgiven what is past, but whosoever commits it again, Allâh will take retribution from him. And Allâh is All&amp;#173;Mighty, All-Able of Retribution." />  <aya id="96" text="Lawful to you is (the pursuit of) water&amp;#173;game and its use for food - for the benefit of yourselves and those who travel, but forbidden is (the pursuit of) land&amp;#173;game as long as you are in a state of &lt;I&gt;Ihrâm &lt;/I&gt;(for &lt;I&gt;Hajj &lt;/I&gt;or '&lt;I&gt;Umrah&lt;/I&gt;). And fear Allâh to Whom you shall be gathered back." />  <aya id="97" text="Allâh has made the Ka'bah, the Sacred House, an asylum of security and &lt;I&gt;Hajj &lt;/I&gt;and '&lt;I&gt;Umrah &lt;/I&gt;(pilgrimage) for mankind, and also the Sacred Month and the animals of offerings and the garlanded (people or animals, etc. marked with the garlands on their necks made from the outer part of the stem of the Makkah trees for their security), that you may know that Allâh has knowledge of all that is in the heavens and all that is in the earth, and that Allâh is the All&amp;#173;Knower of each and everything." />  <aya id="98" text="Know that Allâh is Severe in punishment and that Allâh is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="99" text="The Messenger's duty [i.e. Our Messenger Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; whom We have sent to you, (O mankind)] is but to convey (the Message). And Allâh knows all that you reveal and all that you conceal." />  <aya id="100" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Not equal are &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Khabîth &lt;/I&gt;(all that is evil and bad as regards things, deeds, beliefs, persons, foods, etc.) and &lt;I&gt;At&amp;#173;Taiyib &lt;/I&gt;(all that is good as regards things, deeds, beliefs, persons, foods, etc.), even though the abundance of &lt;I&gt;Al-Khabîth &lt;/I&gt;(evil) may please you.&amp;quot; So fear Allâh much [(abstain from all kinds of sins and evil deeds which He has forbidden) and love Allâh much (perform all kinds of good deeds which He has ordained)], O men of understanding in order that you may be successful." />  <aya id="101" text="O you who believe! Ask not about things which, if made plain to you, may cause you trouble. But if you ask about them while the Qur'ân is being revealed, they will be made plain to you. Allâh has forgiven that, and Allâh is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Forbearing." />  <aya id="102" text="Before you, a community asked such questions, then on that account they became disbelievers." />  <aya id="103" text="Allâh has not instituted things like &lt;I&gt;Bahîrah &lt;/I&gt;(a she&amp;#173;camel whose milk was spared for the idols and nobody was allowed to milk it) or a &lt;I&gt;Sâ'ibah &lt;/I&gt;(a she&amp;#173;camel let loose for free pasture for their false gods, e.g. idols, etc., and nothing was allowed to be carried on it), or a &lt;I&gt;Wasîlah &lt;/I&gt;(a she&amp;#173;camel set free for idols because it has given birth to a she&amp;#173;camel at its first delivery and then again gives birth to a she&amp;#173;camel at its second delivery) or a &lt;I&gt;Hâm &lt;/I&gt;(a stallion&amp;#173;camel freed from work for their idols, after it had finished a number of copulations assigned for it, all these animals were liberated in honour of idols as practised by pagan Arabs in the pre&amp;#173;Islâmic period). But those who disbelieve invent lies against Allâh, and most of them have no understanding." />  <aya id="104" text="And when it is said to them: &amp;quot;Come to what Allâh has revealed and unto the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; for the verdict of that which you have made unlawful).&amp;quot; They say: &amp;quot;Enough for us is that which we found our fathers following,&amp;quot; even though their fathers had no knowledge whatsoever and no guidance." />  <aya id="105" text="O you who believe! Take care of your ownselves, [do righteous deeds, fear Allâh much (abstain from all kinds of sins and evil deeds which He has forbidden) and love Allâh much (perform all kinds of good deeds which He has ordained)]. If you follow the right guidance and enjoin what is right (Islâmic Monotheism and all that Islâm orders one to do) and forbid what is wrong (polytheism, disbelief and all that Islâm has forbidden) no hurt can come to you from those who are in error. The return of you all is to Allâh, then He will inform you about (all) that which you used to do." />  <aya id="106" text="O you who believe! When death approaches any of you, and you make a bequest, then take the testimony of two just men of your own folk or two others from outside, if you are travelling through the land and the calamity of death befalls you. Detain them both after &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (the prayer), (then) if you are in doubt (about their truthfulness), let them both swear by Allâh (saying): &amp;quot;We wish not for any worldly gain in this, even though he (the beneficiary) be our near relative. We shall not hide Testimony of Allâh, for then indeed we should be of the sinful.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="107" text="If then it gets known that these two had been guilty of sin, let two others stand forth in their places, nearest in kin from among those who claim a lawful right. Let them swear by Allâh (saying): &amp;quot;We affirm that our testimony is truer than that of both of them, and that we have not trespassed (the truth), for then indeed we should be of the wrong&amp;#173;doers.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="108" text="That should make it closer (to the fact) that their testimony would be in its true nature and shape (and thus accepted), or else they would fear that (other) oaths would be admitted after their oaths. And fear Allâh and listen ( with obedience to Him). And Allâh guides not the people who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the rebellious and disobedient)." />  <aya id="109" text="On the Day when Allâh will gather the Messengers together and say to them: &amp;quot;What was the response you received (from men to your teaching)? They will say: &amp;quot;We have no knowledge, verily, only You are the All&amp;#173;Knower of all that is hidden (or unseen, etc.).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="110" text="(Remember) when Allâh will say (on the Day of Resurrection). &amp;quot;O 'Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary)! Remember My Favour to you and to your mother when I supported you with &lt;I&gt;Rûh&amp;#173;ul&amp;#173;Qudus &lt;/I&gt;[Jibrael (Gabriel)] so that you spoke to the people in the cradle and in maturity; and when I taught you writing, &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Hikmah &lt;/I&gt;(the power of understanding), the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel); and when you made out of the clay, as it were, the figure of a bird, by My Permission, and you breathed into it, and it became a bird by My Permission, and you healed those born blind, and the lepers by My Permission, and when you brought forth the dead by My Permission; and when I restrained the Children of Israel from you (when they resolved to kill you) since you came unto them with clear proofs, and the disbelievers among them said: 'This is nothing but evident magic.' &amp;quot;" />  <aya id="111" text="And when I (Allâh) put in the hearts of &lt;I&gt;Al-Hawârîeen&lt;/I&gt; (the disciples) [of 'Iesa (Jesus)] to believe in Me and My Messenger, they said: &amp;quot;We believe. And bear witness that we are Muslims.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="112" text="(Remember) when &lt;I&gt;Al-Hawârîûn&lt;/I&gt; (the disciples) said: &amp;quot;O 'Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary)! Can your Lord send down to us a table spread (with food) from heaven?&amp;quot; 'Iesa (Jesus) said: &amp;quot;Fear Allâh, if you are indeed believers.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="113" text="They said: &amp;quot;We wish to eat thereof and to be stronger in Faith, and to know that you have indeed told us the truth and that we ourselves be its witnesses.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="114" text="'Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary), said: &amp;quot;O Allâh, our Lord! Send us from heaven a table spread (with food) that there may be for us - for the first and the last of us - a festival and a sign from You; and provide us sustenance, for You are the Best of sustainers.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="115" text="Allâh said: &amp;quot;I am going to send it down unto you, but if any of you after that disbelieves, then I will punish him with a torment such as I have not inflicted on anyone among (all) the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind and jinns).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="116" text="And (remember) when Allâh will say (on the Day of Resurrection): &amp;quot;O 'Iesa (Jesus), son of Maryam (Mary)! Did you say unto men: 'Worship me and my mother as two gods besides Allâh?' &amp;quot; He will say: &amp;quot;Glory be to You! It was not for me to say what I had no right (to say). Had I said such a thing, You would surely have known it. You know what is in my inner&amp;#173;self though I do not know what is in Yours, truly, You, only You, are the All&amp;#173;Knower of all that is hidden and unseen." />  <aya id="117" text="&amp;quot;Never did I say to them aught except what You (Allâh) did command me to say: 'Worship Allâh, my Lord and your Lord.' And I was a witness over them while I dwelt amongst them, but when You took me up, You were the Watcher over them, and You are a Witness to all things. (This is a great admonition and warning to the Christians of the whole world)." />  <aya id="118" text="&amp;quot;If You punish them, they are Your slaves, and if You forgive them, verily You, only You are the All&amp;#173;Mighty, the All&amp;#173;Wise .&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="119" text="Allâh will say: &amp;quot;This is a Day on which the truthful will profit from their truth: theirs are Gardens under which rivers flow (in Paradise) - they shall abide therein forever. Allâh is pleased with them and they with Him. That is the great success (Paradise)." />  <aya id="120" text="To Allâh belongs the dominion of the heavens and the earth and all that is therein, and He is Able to do all things." /></sura>
