<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><sura id="9">  <aya id="1" text="Freedom from (all) obligations (is declared) from Allâh and His Messenger (&lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) to those of the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, pagans, idolaters, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh), with whom you made a treaty." />  <aya id="2" text="So travel freely (O &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn - &lt;/I&gt;see V.2:105) for four months (as you will) throughout the land, but know that you cannot escape (from the Punishment of) Allâh, and Allâh will disgrace the disbelievers." />  <aya id="3" text="And a declaration from Allâh and His Messenger to mankind on the greatest day (the 10th of Dhul-Hijjah - the 12th month of Islâmic calendar) that Allâh is free from (all) obligations to the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(see V.2:105) and so is His Messenger. So if you (&lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn&lt;/I&gt;) repent, it is better for you, but if you turn away, then know that you cannot escape (from the Punishment of) Allâh. And give tidings (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) of a painful torment to those who disbelieve." />  <aya id="4" text="Except those of the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;with whom you have a treaty, and who have not subsequently failed you in aught, nor have supported anyone against you. So fulfill their treaty to them to the end of their term. Surely Allâh loves &lt;I&gt;Al- Mattaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="5" text="Then when the Sacred Months (the Ist, 7th, 11th, and 12th months of the Islâmic calendar) have passed, then kill the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(see V.2:105) wherever you find them, and capture them and besiege them, and prepare for them each and every ambush. But if they repent and perform &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (&lt;I&gt;Iqâmat-as-Salât&lt;/I&gt;), and give &lt;I&gt;Zakât&lt;/I&gt;, then leave their way free. Verily, Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="6" text="And if anyone of the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, idolaters, pagans, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh) seeks your protection then grant him protection, so that he may hear the Word of Allâh (the Qur'ân), and then escort him to where he can be secure, that is because they are men who know not." />  <aya id="7" text="How can there be a covenant with Allâh and with His Messenger for the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, idolaters, pagans, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh) except those with whom you made a covenant near &lt;I&gt;Al-Masjid-al-Harâm &lt;/I&gt;(at Makkah)? So long, as they are true to you, stand you true to them. Verily, Allâh loves &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)&lt;I&gt;.&lt;/I&gt;" />  <aya id="8" text="How (can there be such a covenant with them) that when you are overpowered by them, they regard not the ties, either of kinship or of covenant with you? With (good words from) their mouths they please you, but their hearts are averse to you, and most of them are &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious, disobedient to Allâh)." />  <aya id="9" text="They have purchased with the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) of Allâh a little gain, and they hindered men from His Way; evil indeed is that which they used to do." />  <aya id="10" text="With regard to a believer, they respect not the ties, either of kinship or of covenant! It is they who are the transgressors." />  <aya id="11" text="But if they repent, perform &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (&lt;I&gt;Iqâmat-as-Salât&lt;/I&gt;) and give &lt;I&gt;Zakât&lt;/I&gt;, then they are your brethren in religion. (In this way) We explain the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) in detail for a people who know." />  <aya id="12" text="But if they violate their oaths after their covenant, and attack your religion with disapproval and criticism then fight (you) the leaders of disbelief (chiefs of Quraish - pagans of Makkah) - for surely their oaths are nothing to them - so that they may stop (evil actions)." />  <aya id="13" text="Will you not fight a people who have violated their oaths (pagans of Makkah) and intended to expel the Messenger, while they did attack you first? Do you fear them? Allâh has more right that you should fear Him, if you are believers." />  <aya id="14" text="Fight against them so that Allâh will punish them by your hands and disgrace them and give you victory over them and heal the breasts of a believing people," />  <aya id="15" text="And remove the anger of their (believers') hearts. Allâh accepts the repentance of whom He wills. Allâh is All-Knowing, All-Wise." />  <aya id="16" text="Do you think that you shall be left alone while Allâh has not yet tested those among you who have striven hard and fought and have not taken &lt;I&gt;Walîjah &lt;/I&gt;[(&lt;I&gt;Batanah &lt;/I&gt;- helpers, advisors and consultants from disbelievers, pagans, etc.) giving openly to them their secrets] besides Allâh and His Messenger, and the believers. Allâh is Well-Acquainted with what you do." />  <aya id="17" text="It is not for the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, idolaters, pagans, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh), to maintain the Mosques of Allâh (i.e. to pray and worship Allâh therein, to look after their cleanliness and their building, etc.), while they witness against their ownselves of disbelief. The works of such are in vain and in Fire shall they abide." />  <aya id="18" text="The Mosques of Allâh shall be maintained only by those who believe in Allâh and the Last Day; perform &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (&lt;I&gt;Iqâmat-as-Salât&lt;/I&gt;), and give &lt;I&gt;Zakât &lt;/I&gt;and fear none but Allâh. It is they who are expected to be on true guidance." />  <aya id="19" text="Do you consider the providing of drinking water to the pilgrims and the maintenance of &lt;I&gt;Al-Masjid-al-Harâm &lt;/I&gt;(at Makkah) as equal to the worth of those who believe in Allâh and the Last Day, and strive hard and fight in the Cause of Allâh? They are not equal before Allâh. And Allâh guides not those people who are the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn&lt;/I&gt; (polytheists and wrong-doers)." />  <aya id="20" text="Those who believed (in the Oneness of Allâh - Islâmic Monotheism) and emigrated and strove hard and fought in Allâh's Cause with their wealth and their lives are far higher in degree with Allâh. They are the successful." />  <aya id="21" text="Their Lord gives them glad tidings of a Mercy from Him, and that He is pleased (with them), and of Gardens (Paradise) for them wherein are everlasting delights." />  <aya id="22" text="They will dwell therein forever. Verily, with Allâh is a great reward." />  <aya id="23" text="O you who believe! Take not for &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;(supporters and helpers) your fathers and your brothers if they prefer disbelief to Belief. And whoever of you does so, then he is one of the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(wrong-doers, etc.)." />  <aya id="24" text="Say: If your fathers, your sons, your brothers, your wives, your kindred, the wealth that you have gained, the commerce in which you fear a decline, and the dwellings in which you delight &amp;#133; are dearer to you than Allâh and His Messenger, and striving hard and fighting in His Cause , then wait until Allâh brings about His Decision (torment). And Allâh guides not the people who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the rebellious, disobedient to Allâh)." />  <aya id="25" text="Truly Allâh has given you victory on many battle fields, and on the Day of Hunain (battle) when you rejoiced at your great number but it availed you naught and the earth, vast as it is, was straitened for you, then you turned back in flight." />  <aya id="26" text="Then Allâh did send down His &lt;I&gt;Sakînah &lt;/I&gt;(calmness, tranquillity and reassurance, etc.) on the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), and on the believers, and sent down forces (angels) which you saw not, and punished the disbelievers. Such is the recompense of disbelievers." />  <aya id="27" text="Then after that Allâh will accept the repentance of whom He will. And Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="28" text="O you who believe (in Allâh's Oneness and in His Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)! Verily, the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, pagans, idolaters, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh, and in the Message of Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) are &lt;I&gt;Najasun &lt;/I&gt;(impure) . So let them not come near &lt;I&gt;Al-Masjid-al-Harâm &lt;/I&gt;(at Makkah) after this year, and if you fear poverty, Allâh will enrich you if He will, out of His Bounty. Surely, Allâh is All-Knowing, All-Wise." />  <aya id="29" text="Fight against those who (1) believe not in Allâh, (2) nor in the Last Day, (3) nor forbid that which has been forbidden by Allâh and His Messenger (4) and those who acknowledge not the religion of truth (i.e. Islâm) among the people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians), until they pay the &lt;I&gt;Jizyah&lt;/I&gt; with willing submission, and feel themselves subdued." />  <aya id="30" text="And the Jews say: 'Uzair (Ezra) is the son of Allâh, and the Christians say: Messiah is the son of Allâh. That is a saying from their mouths. They imitate the saying of the disbelievers of old. Allâh's Curse be on them, how they are deluded away from the truth!" />  <aya id="31" text="They (Jews and Christians) took their rabbis and their monks to be their lords besides Allâh (by obeying them in things which they made lawful or unlawful according to their own desires without being ordered by Allâh), and (they also took as their Lord) Messiah, son of Maryam (Mary), while they (Jews and Christians) were commanded [in the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel)) to worship none but One &lt;I&gt;Ilâh&lt;/I&gt; (God - Allâh) &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâha illa Huwa &lt;/I&gt;(none has the right to be worshipped but He) . Praise and glory be to Him, (far above is He) from having the partners they associate (with Him).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="32" text="They (the disbelievers, the Jews and the Christians) want to extinguish Allâh's Light (with which Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; has been sent &lt;I&gt;- &lt;/I&gt;Islâmic Monotheism) with their mouths, but Allâh will not allow except that His Light should be perfected even though the &lt;I&gt;Kâfirûn &lt;/I&gt;(disbelievers) hate (it)." />  <aya id="33" text="It is He Who has sent His Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) with guidance and the religion of truth (Islâm), to make it superior over all religions even though the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, pagans, idolaters, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh) hate (it)." />  <aya id="34" text="O you who believe! Verily, there are many of the (Jewish) rabbis and the (Christian) monks who devour the wealth of mankind in falsehood, and hinder (them) from the Way of Allâh (i.e. Allâh's Religion of Islâmic Monotheism). And those who hoard up gold and silver [&lt;I&gt;Al-Kanz&lt;/I&gt;:&lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;the money, the &lt;I&gt;Zakât &lt;/I&gt;of which has not been paid], and spend it not in the Way of Allâh, -announce unto them a painful torment." />  <aya id="35" text="On the Day when that (&lt;I&gt;Al-Kanz&lt;/I&gt;: money, gold and silver, etc., the &lt;I&gt;Zakât &lt;/I&gt;of which has not been paid) will be heated in the Fire of Hell and with it will be branded their foreheads, their flanks, and their backs, (and it will be said unto them):-&amp;quot;This is the treasure which you hoarded for yourselves. Now taste of what you used to hoard.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="36" text="Verily, the number of months with Allâh is twelve months (in a year), so was it ordained by Allâh on the Day when He created the heavens and the earth; of them four are Sacred, (i.e. the 1st, the 7th, the 11th and the 12th months of the Islâmic calendar). That is the right religion, so wrong not yourselves therein, and fight against the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, pagans, idolaters, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh) collectively , as they fight against you collectively. But know that Allâh is with those who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="37" text="The postponing (of a Sacred Month) is indeed an addition to disbelief: thereby the disbelievers are led astray, for they make it lawful one year and forbid it another year in order to adjust the number of months forbidden by Allâh, and make such forbidden ones lawful. The evil of their deeds seems pleasing to them. And Allâh guides not the people, who disbelieve." />  <aya id="38" text="O you who believe! What is the matter with you, that when you are asked to march forth in the Cause of Allâh (i.e. &lt;I&gt;Jihâd&lt;/I&gt;) you cling heavily to the earth? Are you pleased with the life of this world rather than the Hereafter? But little is the enjoyment of the life of this world as compared with the Hereafter." />  <aya id="39" text="If you march not forth, He will punish you with a painful torment and will replace you by another people, and you cannot harm Him at all, and Allâh is Able to do all things." />  <aya id="40" text="If you help him (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) not (it does not matter), for Allâh did indeed help him when the disbelievers drove him out, the second of two, when they (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; and Abu Bakr ÑÖì &lt;&lt;code2&gt;&gt; &lt;&lt;codeb&gt;&gt;) were in the cave, and he (&lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) said to his companion (Abu Bakr ÑÖì &lt;&lt;code2&gt;&gt; &lt;&lt;codeb&gt;&gt;): &amp;quot;Be not sad (or afraid), surely Allâh is with us.&amp;quot; Then Allâh sent down His &lt;I&gt;Sakînah &lt;/I&gt;(calmness, tranquillity, peace, etc.) upon him, and strengthened him with forces (angels) which you saw not, and made the word of those who disbelieved the lowermost, while it was the Word of Allâh that became the uppermost, and Allâh is All-Mighty, All-Wise." />  <aya id="41" text="March forth, whether you are light (being healthy, young and wealthy) or heavy (being ill, old and poor), strive hard with your wealth and your lives in the Cause of Allâh. This is better for you, if you but knew." />  <aya id="42" text="Had it been a near gain (booty in front of them) and an easy journey, they would have followed you, but the distance (Tabuk expedition) was long for them, and they would swear by Allâh, &amp;quot;If we only could, we would certainly have come forth with you.&amp;quot; They destroy their ownselves, and Allâh knows that they are liars." />  <aya id="43" text="May Allâh forgive you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;). Why did you grant them leave (for remaining behind, you should have persisted as regards your order to them to proceed on &lt;I&gt;Jihâd&lt;/I&gt;), until those who told the truth were seen by you in a clear light, and you had known the liars?" />  <aya id="44" text="Those who believe in Allâh and the Last Day would not ask your leave to be exempted from fighting with their properties and their lives, and Allâh is the All-Knower of &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="45" text="It is only those who believe not in Allâh and the Last Day and whose hearts are in doubt that ask your leave (to be exempted from &lt;I&gt;Jihâd&lt;/I&gt;). So in their doubts they waver." />  <aya id="46" text="And if they had intended to march out, certainly, they would have made some preparation for it, but Allâh was averse to their being sent forth, so He made them lag behind, and it was said (to them), &amp;quot;Sit you among those who sit (at home).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="47" text="Had they marched out with you, they would have added to you nothing except disorder, and they would have hurried about in your midst (spreading corruption) and sowing sedition among you, and there are some among you who would have listened to them. And Allâh is the All-Knower of the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong-doers, etc.)." />  <aya id="48" text="Verily, they had plotted sedition before, and had upset matters for you, - until the truth (victory) came and the Decree of Allâh (His Religion, Islâm) became manifest though they hated it." />  <aya id="49" text="And among them is he who says:&amp;quot;Grant me leave (to be exempted from &lt;I&gt;Jihâd&lt;/I&gt;) and put me not into trial.&amp;quot; Surely, they have fallen into trial. And verily, Hell is surrounding the disbelievers." />  <aya id="50" text="If good befalls you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), it grieves them, but if a calamity overtakes you, they say: &amp;quot;We took our precaution beforehand,&amp;quot; and they turn away rejoicing." />  <aya id="51" text="Say: &amp;quot;Nothing shall ever happen to us except what Allâh has ordained for us. He is our &lt;I&gt;Maulâ &lt;/I&gt;(Lord, Helper and Protector).&amp;quot; And in Allâh let the believers put their trust." />  <aya id="52" text="Say: &amp;quot;Do you wait for us (anything) except one of the two best things (martyrdom or victory); while we await for you either that Allâh will afflict you with a punishment from Himself or at our hands. So wait, we too are waiting with you.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="53" text="Say: &amp;quot;Spend (in Allâh's Cause) willingly or unwillingly, it will not be accepted from you. Verily, you are ever a people who are &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious, disobedient to Allâh).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="54" text="And nothing prevents their contributions from being accepted from them except that they disbelieved in Allâh and in His Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;); and that they came not to &lt;I&gt;As-Salât &lt;/I&gt;(the prayer) except in a lazy state ; and that they offer not contributions but unwillingly." />  <aya id="55" text="So let not their wealth or their children amaze you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;); in reality Allâh's Plan is to punish them with these things in the life of the this world, and that their souls shall depart (die) while they are disbelievers." />  <aya id="56" text="They swear by Allâh that they are truly of you while they are not of you, but they are a people (hypocrites) who are afraid (that you may kill them)." />  <aya id="57" text="Should they find a refuge, or caves, or a place of concealment, they would turn straightway thereto with a swift rush." />  <aya id="58" text="And of them are some who accuse you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) in the matter of (the distribution of) the alms. If they are given part thereof, they are pleased, but if they are not given thereof, behold! They are enraged!" />  <aya id="59" text="Would that they were contented with what Allâh and His Messenger (&lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) gave them and had said: &amp;quot;Allâh is Sufficient for us. Allâh will give us of His Bounty, and (also) His Messenger (from alms, etc.). We implore Allâh (to enrich us).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="60" text="&lt;I&gt;As-Sadaqât &lt;/I&gt;(here it means &lt;I&gt;Zakât&lt;/I&gt;) are only for the &lt;I&gt;Fuqarâ'&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;(poor), and &lt;I&gt;Al-Masâkin&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;(the poor) and those employed to collect (the funds); and for to attract the hearts of those who have been inclined (towards Islâm); and to free the captives; and for those in debt; and for Allâh's Cause (i.e. for &lt;I&gt;Mujâhidûn &lt;/I&gt;- those fighting in the holy wars), and for the wayfarer (a traveller who is cut off from everything); a duty imposed by Allâh. And Allâh is All-Knower, All-Wise." />  <aya id="61" text="And among them are men who hurt the Prophet (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and say: &amp;quot;He is (lending his) ear (to every news).&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;He listens to what is best for you; he believes in Allâh; has faith in the believers; and is a mercy to those of you who believe.&amp;quot; But those who hurt Allâh's Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) will have a painful torment." />  <aya id="62" text="They swear by Allâh to you (Muslims) in order to please you, but it is more fitting that they should please Allâh and His Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), if they are believers." />  <aya id="63" text="Know they not that whoever opposes and shows hostility to Allâh (ÚÒ æ Ìá) and His Messenger (&lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), certainly for him will be the Fire of Hell to abide therein. That is extreme disgrace." />  <aya id="64" text="The hypocrites fear lest a &lt;I&gt;Sûrah &lt;/I&gt;(chapter of the Qur'ân) should be revealed about them, showing them what is in their hearts. Say: &amp;quot;(Go ahead and) mock! But certainly Allâh will bring to light all that you fear.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="65" text="If you ask them (about this), they declare: &amp;quot;We were only talking idly and joking.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Was it at Allâh (ÚÒ æ Ìá), and His &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) and His Messenger (&lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) that you were mocking?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="66" text="Make no excuse; you have disbelieved after you had believed. If We pardon some of you, We will punish others amongst you because they were &lt;I&gt;Mujrimûn &lt;/I&gt;(disbelievers, polytheists, sinners, criminals, etc.)." />  <aya id="67" text="The hypocrites, men and women, are from one another, they enjoin (on the people) &lt;I&gt;Al-Munkar &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. disbelief and polytheism of all kinds and all that Islâm has forbidden), and forbid (people) from &lt;I&gt;Al-Ma'rûf &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. Islâmic Monotheism and all that Islâm orders one to do), and they close their hands [from giving (spending in Allâh's Cause) alms, etc.]. They have forgotten Allâh, so He has forgotten them. Verily, the hypocrites are the &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious, disobedient to Allâh)." />  <aya id="68" text="Allâh has promised the hypocrites; men and women, and the disbelievers, the Fire of Hell, therein shall they abide. It will suffice them. Allâh has cursed them and for them is the lasting torment." />  <aya id="69" text="Like those before you, they were mightier than you in power, and more abundant in wealth and children. They had enjoyed their portion awhile, so enjoy your portion awhile as those before you enjoyed their portion awhile; and you indulged in play and pastime (and in telling lies against Allâh and His Messenger Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) as they indulged in play and pastime. Such are they whose deeds are in vain in this world and in the Hereafter. Such are they who are the losers." />  <aya id="70" text="Has not the story reached them of those before them? - The people of Nûh (Noah), 'Ad, and Thamûd, the people of Ibrahîm (Abraham), the dwellers of Madyan (Midian) and the cities overthrown [i.e. the people to whom Lout (Lot) preached], to them came their Messengers with clear proofs. So it was not Allâh Who wronged them, but they used to wrong themselves." />  <aya id="71" text="The believers, men and women, are &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;(helpers, supporters, friends, protectors) of one another, they enjoin (on the people) &lt;I&gt;Al-Ma'rûf &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. Islâmic Monotheism and all that Islâm orders one to do), and forbid (people) from &lt;I&gt;Al-Munkar &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. polytheism and disbelief of all kinds, and all that Islâm has forbidden); they perform &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (&lt;I&gt;Iqâmat-as-Salât&lt;/I&gt;) and give the &lt;I&gt;Zakât, &lt;/I&gt;and obey Allâh and His Messenger. Allâh will have His Mercy on them. Surely Allâh is All-Mighty, All-Wise." />  <aya id="72" text="Allâh has promised to the believers -men and women, - Gardens under which rivers flow to dwell therein forever, and beautiful mansions in Gardens of &lt;I&gt;'Adn &lt;/I&gt;(Eden&lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;Paradise). But the greatest bliss is the Good Pleasure of Allâh. That is the supreme success." />  <aya id="73" text="O Prophet (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)! Strive hard against the disbelievers and the hypocrites, and be harsh against them, their abode is Hell, - and worst indeed is that destination." />  <aya id="74" text="They swear by Allâh that they said nothing (bad), but really they said the word of disbelief, and they disbelieved after accepting Islâm, and they resolved that (plot to murder Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) which they were unable to carry out, and they could not find any cause to do so except that Allâh and His Messenger had enriched them of His Bounty. If then they repent, it will be better for them, but if they turn away, Allâh will punish them with a painful torment in this worldly life and in the Hereafter. And there is none for them on earth as a &lt;I&gt;Walî &lt;/I&gt;(supporter, protector) or a helper." />  <aya id="75" text="And of them are some who made a covenant with Allâh (saying): &amp;quot;If He bestowed on us of His Bounty, we will verily, give &lt;I&gt;Sadaqâh &lt;/I&gt;(&lt;I&gt;Zakât&lt;/I&gt; and voluntary charity in Allâh's Cause) and will be certainly among those who are righteous.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="76" text="Then when He gave them of His Bounty, they became niggardly [refused to pay the &lt;I&gt;Sadaqâh &lt;/I&gt;(&lt;I&gt;Zakât&lt;/I&gt; or voluntary charity)], and turned away, averse." />  <aya id="77" text="So He punished them by putting hypocrisy into their hearts till the Day whereon they shall meet Him, because they broke that (covenant with Allâh) which they had promised Him and because they used to tell lies." />  <aya id="78" text="Know they not that Allâh knows their secret ideas, and their &lt;I&gt;Najwa&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;(secret counsels), and that Allâh is the All-Knower of the unseen." />  <aya id="79" text="Those who defame such of the believers who give charity (in Allâh's Cause) voluntarily, and those who could not find to give charity (in Allâh's Cause) except what is available to them, so they mock at them (believers), Allâh will throw back their mockery on them, and they shall have a painful torment." />  <aya id="80" text="Whether you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) ask forgiveness for them (hypocrites) or ask not forgiveness for them &amp;#133; (and even) if you ask seventy times for their forgiveness &amp;#133; Allâh will not forgive them, because they have disbelieved in Allâh and His Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;). And Allâh guides not those people who are &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious, disobedient to Allâh)." />  <aya id="81" text="Those who stayed away (from Tabuk expedition) rejoiced in their staying behind the Messenger of Allâh; they hated to strive and fight with their properties and their lives in the Cause of Allâh, and they said: &amp;quot;March not forth in the heat.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;The Fire of Hell is more intense in heat&amp;quot;, if only they could understand!" />  <aya id="82" text="So let them laugh a little and (they will) cry much as a recompense of what they used to earn (by committing sins)." />  <aya id="83" text="If Allâh brings you back to a party of them (the hypocrites), and they ask your permission to go out (to fight), say: &amp;quot;Never shall you go out with me, nor fight an enemy with me; you agreed to sit inactive on the first occasion, then you sit (now) with those who lag behind.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="84" text="And never (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) pray (funeral prayer) for any of them (hypocrites) who dies, nor stand at his grave. Certainly they disbelieved in Allâh and His Messenger, and died while they were &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious, - disobedient to Allâh and His Messenger &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)." />  <aya id="85" text="And let not their wealth or their children amaze you. Allâh's Plan is to punish them with these things in this world, and that their souls shall depart (die) while they are disbelievers." />  <aya id="86" text="And when a &lt;I&gt;Sûrah &lt;/I&gt;(chapter from the Qur'ân) is revealed, enjoining them to believe in Allâh and to strive hard and fight along with His Messenger, the wealthy among them ask your leave to exempt them (from &lt;I&gt;Jihâd&lt;/I&gt;) and say, &amp;quot;Leave us (behind), we would be with those who sit (at home).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="87" text="They are content to be with those (the women) who sit behind (at home). Their hearts are sealed up (from all kinds of goodness and right guidance), so they understand not." />  <aya id="88" text="But the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and those who believed with him (in Islâmic Monotheism) strove hard and fought with their wealth and their lives (in Allâh's Cause). Such are they for whom are the good things, and it is they who will be successful." />  <aya id="89" text="For them Allâh has got ready Gardens (Paradise) under which rivers flow, to dwell therein forever. That is the supreme success." />  <aya id="90" text="And those who made excuses from the bedouins came (to you, O Prophet &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) asking your permission to exempt them (from the battle), and those who had lied to Allâh and His Messenger sat at home (without asking the permission for it); a painful torment will seize those of them who disbelieve." />  <aya id="91" text="There is no blame on those who are weak or ill or who find no resources to spend [in holy fighting (&lt;I&gt;Jihâd&lt;/I&gt;)], if they are sincere and true (in duty) to Allâh and His Messenger. No ground (of complaint) can there be against the &lt;I&gt;Muhsinûn &lt;/I&gt;(good-doers - see the footnote of V.9:120). And Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="92" text="Nor (is there blame) on those who came to you to be provided with mounts, and when you said: &amp;quot;I can find no mounts for you,&amp;quot; they turned back, while their eyes overflowing with tears of grief that they could not find anything to spend (for &lt;I&gt;Jihâd&lt;/I&gt;)." />  <aya id="93" text="The ground (of complaint) is only against those who are rich, and yet ask exemption . They are content to be with (the women) who sit behind (at home) and Allâh has sealed up their hearts (from all kinds of goodness and right guidance) so that they know not (what they are losing)." />  <aya id="94" text="They (the hypocrites) will present their excuses to you (Muslims), when you return to them. Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) &amp;quot;Present no excuses, we shall not believe you. Allâh has already informed us of the news concerning you. Allâh and His Messenger will observe your deeds. In the end you will be brought back to the All-Knower of the unseen and the seen, then He (Allâh) will inform you of what you used to do.&amp;quot; [&lt;I&gt;Tafsir At-Tabari&lt;/I&gt;]" />  <aya id="95" text="They will swear by Allâh to you (Muslims) when you return to them, that you may turn away from them. So turn away from them. Surely, they are &lt;I&gt;Rijsun &lt;/I&gt;[i.e. &lt;I&gt;Najasun&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;(impure) because of their evil deeds], and Hell is their dwelling place, - a recompense for that which they used to earn." />  <aya id="96" text="They (the hypocrites) swear to you (Muslims) that you may be pleased with them, but if you are pleased with them, certainly Allâh is not pleased with the people who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious, disobedient to Allâh)." />  <aya id="97" text="The bedouins are the worst in disbelief and hypocrisy, and more likely to be in ignorance of the limits (Allâh's Commandments and His Legal Laws, etc.) which Allâh has revealed to His Messenger. And Allâh is All-Knower, All-Wise." />  <aya id="98" text="And of the bedouins there are some who look upon what they spend (in Allâh's Cause) as a fine and watch for calamities for you, on them be the calamity of evil. And Allâh is All-Hearer, All-Knower." />  <aya id="99" text="And of the bedouins there are some who believe in Allâh and the Last Day, and look upon what they spend in Allâh's Cause as approaches to Allâh, and a cause of receiving the Messenger's invocations. Indeed these (spendings in Allâh's Cause) are an approach for them. Allâh will admit them to His Mercy. Certainly Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="100" text="And the first to embrace Islâm of the &lt;I&gt;Muhâjirûn &lt;/I&gt;(those who migrated from Makkah to Al-Madinah) and the &lt;I&gt;Ansâr &lt;/I&gt;(the citizens of Al-Madinah who helped and gave aid to the &lt;I&gt;Muhâjirûn&lt;/I&gt;) and also those who followed them exactly (in Faith). Allâh is well-pleased with them as they are well-pleased with Him. He has prepared for them Gardens under which rivers flow (Paradise), to dwell therein forever. That is the supreme success." />  <aya id="101" text="And among the bedouins round about you, some are hypocrites, and so are some among the people of Al-Madinah, they exaggerate and persist in hypocrisy, you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) know them not, We know them. We shall punish them twice, and thereafter they shall be brought back to a great (horrible) torment." />  <aya id="102" text="And (there are) others who have acknowledged their sins, they have mixed a deed that was righteous with another that was evil. Perhaps Allâh will turn unto them in forgiveness. Surely, Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful ." />  <aya id="103" text="Take &lt;I&gt;Sadaqah &lt;/I&gt;(alms) from their wealth in order to purify them and sanctify them with it, and invoke Allâh for them. Verily! Your invocations are a source of security for them, and Allâh is All-Hearer, All-Knower." />  <aya id="104" text="Know they not that Allâh accepts repentance from His slaves and takes the &lt;I&gt;Sadaqât &lt;/I&gt;(alms, charities) and that All&amp;achrc;h Alone is the One Who forgives and accepts repentance, Most Merciful?" />  <aya id="105" text="And say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) &amp;quot;Do deeds! Allâh will see your deeds, and (so will) His Messenger and the believers. And you will be brought back to the All-Knower of the unseen and the seen. Then He will inform you of what you used to do.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="106" text="And others await Allâh's Decree, whether He will punish them or will forgive them. And Allâh is All-Knowing, All-Wise." />  <aya id="107" text="And as for those who put up a mosque by way of harming and disbelief, and to disunite the believers, and as an outpost for those who warred against Allâh and His Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) aforetime, they will indeed swear that their intention is nothing but good. Allâh bears witness that they are certainly liars." />  <aya id="108" text="Never stand you therein. Verily, the mosque whose foundation was laid from the first day on piety is more worthy that you stand therein (to pray). In it are men who love to clean and to purify themselves. And Allâh loves those who make themselves clean and pure (i.e. who clean their private parts with dust [i.e. to be considered as soap) and water from urine and stools, after answering the call of nature]." />  <aya id="109" text="Is it then he, who laid the foundation of his building on piety to Allâh and His Good Pleasure, better, or he who laid the foundation of his building on an undetermined brink of a precipice ready to crumble down, so that it crumbled to pieces with him into the Fire of Hell. And Allâh guides not the people who are the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(cruel, violent, proud, polytheist and wrong-doer)." />  <aya id="110" text="The building which they built will never cease to be a cause of hypocrisy and doubt in their hearts, unless their hearts are cut to pieces. (i.e. till they die). And Allâh is All-Knowing, All-Wise." />  <aya id="111" text="Verily, Allâh has purchased of the believers their lives and their properties; for the price that theirs shall be the Paradise. They fight in Allâh's Cause, so they kill (others) and are killed. It is a promise in truth which is binding on Him in the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel) and the Qur'ân. And who is truer to his covenant than Allâh? Then rejoice in the bargain which you have concluded. That is the supreme success ." />  <aya id="112" text="(The believers whose lives Allâh has purchased are) those who repent to Allâh (from polytheism and hypocrisy, etc.), who worship Him, who praise Him, who fast (or go out in Allâh's Cause), who bow down (in prayer), who prostrate themselves (in prayer), who enjoin (people) for &lt;I&gt;Al-Ma'rûf &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. Islâmic Monotheism and all what Islâm has ordained) and forbid (people) from &lt;I&gt;Al-Munkar &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. disbelief, polytheism of all kinds and all that Islâm has forbidden), and who observe the limits set by Allâh (do all that Allâh has ordained and abstain from all kinds of sins and evil deeds which Allâh has forbidden). And give glad tidings to the believers." />  <aya id="113" text="It is not (proper) for the Prophet and those who believe to ask Allâh's Forgiveness for the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, idolaters, pagans, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh) even though they be of kin, after it has become clear to them that they are the dwellers of the Fire (because they died in a state of disbelief)." />  <aya id="114" text="And [Ibrahîm's (Abraham)] invoking (of Allâh) for his father's forgiveness was only because of a promise he [Ibrahîm (Abraham)] had made to him (his father). But when it became clear to him [Ibrahîm (Abraham)] that he (his father) is an enemy to Allâh, he dissociated himself from him. Verily Ibrahîm (Abraham) was &lt;I&gt;Al-Awwah &lt;/I&gt;(has fifteen different meanings but the correct one seems to be that he used to invoke Allâh with humility, glorify Him and remember Him much), and was forbearing. (&lt;I&gt;Tafsir Al-Qurtubî&lt;/I&gt;)." />  <aya id="115" text="And Allâh will never lead a people astray after He has guided them until He makes clear to them as to what they should avoid. Verily, Allâh is the All-Knower of everything." />  <aya id="116" text="Verily, Allâh! Unto Him belongs the dominion of the heavens and the earth, He gives life and He causes death. And besides Allâh you have neither any &lt;I&gt;Walî&lt;/I&gt; (protector or guardian) nor any helper." />  <aya id="117" text="Allâh has forgiven the Prophet (&lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), the &lt;I&gt;Muhajirûn &lt;/I&gt;(Muslim emigrants who left their homes and came to Al-Madinah) and the &lt;I&gt;Ansar &lt;/I&gt;(Muslims of Al-Madinah) who followed him (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) in the time of distress (Tabûk expedition, etc.), after the hearts of a party of them had nearly deviated (from the Right Path), but He accepted their repentance. Certainly, He is unto them full of Kindness, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="118" text="And (He did forgive also) the three [who did not join the Tabûk expedition (whom the Prophet &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)] left (i.e. he did not give his judgement in their case, and their case was suspended for Allâh's Decision) till for them the earth, vast as it is, was straitened and their ownselves were straitened to them, and they perceived that there is no fleeing from Allâh, and no refuge but with Him. Then, He accepted their repentance, that they might repent (unto Him). Verily, Allâh is the One Who accepts repentance, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="119" text="O you who believe! Be afraid of Allâh, and be with those who are true (in words and deeds) ." />  <aya id="120" text="It was not becoming of the people of Al-Madinah and the bedouins of the neighbourhood to remain behind Allâh's Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; when fighting in Allâh's Cause) and (it was not becoming of them) to prefer their own lives to his life. That is because they suffer neither thirst nor fatigue, nor hunger in the Cause of Allâh, nor they take any step to raise the anger of disbelievers nor inflict any injury upon an enemy but is written to their credit as a deed of righteousness. Surely, Allâh wastes not the reward of the &lt;I&gt;Muhsinûn&lt;/I&gt;" />  <aya id="121" text="Nor do they spend anything (in Allâh's Cause) - small or great - nor cross a valley, but is written to their credit, that Allâh may recompense them with the best of what they used to do (i.e. Allâh will reward their good deeds according to the reward of their best deeds which they did in the most perfect manner)." />  <aya id="122" text="And it is not (proper) for the believers to go out to fight (&lt;I&gt;Jihâd&lt;/I&gt;) all together. Of every troop of them, a party only should go forth, that they (who are left behind) may get instructions in (Islâmic) religion, and that they may warn their people when they return to them, so that they may beware (of evil)." />  <aya id="123" text="O you who believe! Fight those of the disbelievers who are close to you, and let them find harshness in you, and know that Allâh is with those who are the &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="124" text="And whenever there comes down a &lt;I&gt;Sûrah &lt;/I&gt;(chapter from the Qur'ân), some of them (hypocrites) say: &amp;quot;Which of you has had his Faith increased by it?&amp;quot; As for those who believe, it has increased their Faith, and they rejoice." />  <aya id="125" text="But as for those in whose hearts is a disease (of doubt, disbelief and hypocrisy), it will add suspicion and doubt to their suspicion, disbelief and doubt, and they die while they are disbelievers." />  <aya id="126" text="See they not that they are tried once or twice every year (with different kinds of calamities, disease, famine, etc.)? Yet, they turn not in repentance, nor do they learn a lesson (from it)." />  <aya id="127" text="And whenever there comes down a &lt;I&gt;Sûrah&lt;/I&gt; (chapter from the Qur'ân), they look at one another (saying): &amp;quot;Does any one see you?&amp;quot; Then they turn away. Allâh has turned their hearts (from the light) because they are a people that understand not." />  <aya id="128" text="Verily, there has come unto you a Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) from amongst yourselves (i.e. whom you know well). It grieves him that you should receive any injury or difficulty. He (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) is anxious over you (to be rightly guided, to repent to Allâh, and beg Him to pardon and forgive your sins, in order that you may enter Paradise and be saved from the punishment of the Hell-fire), for the believers (he &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; is) full of pity, kind, and merciful." />  <aya id="129" text=". But if they turn away, say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Allâh is sufficient for me. &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâha illa Huwa &lt;/I&gt;(none has the right to be worshipped but He), in Him I put my trust and He is the Lord of the Mighty Throne.&amp;quot;" /></sura>
