<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><sura id="3">  <aya id="1" text="&lt;I&gt;Alif-Lâm-Mîm&lt;/I&gt;. [These letters are one of the miracles of the Qur'ân, and none but Allâh (Alone) knows their meanings]." />  <aya id="2" text="Allâh! &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilahâ illa Huwa&lt;/I&gt; (none has the right to be worshipped but He), the Ever Living, the One Who sustains and protects all that exists." />  <aya id="3" text="It is He Who has sent down the Book (the Qur'ân) to you (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) with truth, confirming what came before it. And he sent down the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel)." />  <aya id="4" text="Aforetime, as a guidance to mankind, And He sent down the criterion [of judgement between right and wrong (this Qur'ân)]. Truly, those who disbelieve in the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) of Allâh, for them there is a severe torment; and Allâh is All-Mighty, All-Able of Retribution." />  <aya id="5" text="Truly, nothing is hidden from Allâh, in the earth or in the heavens." />  <aya id="6" text="He it is Who shapes you in the wombs as He pleases. &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâha illa Huwa&lt;/I&gt; (none has the right to be worshipped but He), the All-Mighty, the All-Wise." />  <aya id="7" text="It is He Who has sent down to you (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) the Book (this Qur'ân). In it are Verses that are entirely clear, they are the foundations of the Book [and those are the Verses of &lt;I&gt;Al-Ahkâm &lt;/I&gt;(commandments, etc.), &lt;I&gt;Al-Farâ'id &lt;/I&gt;(obligatory duties) and &lt;I&gt;Al-Hudud &lt;/I&gt;(legal laws for the punishment of thieves, adulterers, etc.)]; and others not entirely clear. So as for those in whose hearts there is a deviation (from the truth) they follow that which is not entirely clear thereof, seeking &lt;I&gt;Al-Fitnah &lt;/I&gt;(polytheism and trials, etc.), and seeking for its hidden meanings, but none knows its hidden meanings save Allâh. And those who are firmly grounded in knowledge say: &amp;quot;We believe in it; the whole of it (clear and unclear Verses) are from our Lord.&amp;quot; And none receive admonition except men of understanding. (&lt;I&gt;Tafsir At-Tabarî&lt;/I&gt;)." />  <aya id="8" text="(They say): &amp;quot;Our Lord! Let not our hearts deviate (from the truth) after You have guided us, and grant us mercy from You. Truly, You are the Bestower.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="9" text="Our Lord! Verily, it is You Who will gather mankind together on the Day about which there is no doubt. Verily, Allâh never breaks His Promise&amp;quot;." />  <aya id="10" text="Verily, those who disbelieve, neither their properties nor their offspring will avail them whatsoever against Allâh; and it is they who will be fuel of the Fire." />  <aya id="11" text="Like the behaviour of the people of Fir'aun (Pharaoh) and those before them; they belied Our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.), so Allâh seized (destroyed) them for their sins. And Allâh is Severe in punishment." />  <aya id="12" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) to those who disbelieve: &amp;quot;You will be defeated and gathered together to Hell, and worst indeed is that place to rest.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="13" text="There has already been a sign for you (O Jews) in the two armies that met (in combat i.e. the battle of Badr): One was fighting in the Cause of Allâh, and as for the other (they) were disbelievers. They (the believers) saw them (the disbelievers) with their own eyes twice their number (although they were thrice their number). And Allâh supports with His Victory whom He pleases. Verily, in this is a lesson for those who understand. (See Verse 8:44). (&lt;I&gt;Tafsir At-Tabarî&lt;/I&gt;)" />  <aya id="14" text="Beautified for men is the love of things they covet; women, children, much of gold and silver (wealth), branded beautiful horses, cattle and well-tilled land. This is the pleasure of the present world's life; but Allâh has the excellent return (Paradise with flowing rivers, etc.) with Him." />  <aya id="15" text="Say: &amp;quot;Shall I inform you of things far better than those? For &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2) there are Gardens (Paradise) with their Lord, underneath which rivers flow. Therein (is their) eternal (home) and &lt;I&gt;Azwâjun Mutahharatun&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;(purified mates or wives) [i.e. they will have no menses, urine, or stool, etc.], And Allâh will be pleased with them. And Allâh is All-Seer of the (His) slaves&amp;quot;." />  <aya id="16" text="Those who say: &amp;quot;Our Lord! We have indeed believed, so forgive us our sins and save us from the punishment of the Fire.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="17" text="(They are) those who are patient ones, those who are true (in Faith, words, and deeds), and obedient with sincere devotion in worship to Allâh. Those who spend [give the &lt;I&gt;Zakât &lt;/I&gt;and alms in the Way of Allâh] and those who pray and beg Allâh's Pardon in the last hours of the night." />  <aya id="18" text="Allâh bears witness that &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâha illa Huwa&lt;/I&gt; (none has the right to be worshipped but He), and the angels, and those having knowledge (also give this witness); (He is always) maintaining His creation in Justice. &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâh illa Huwa&lt;/I&gt; (none has the right to be worshipped but He), the All-Mighty, the All-Wise." />  <aya id="19" text="Truly, the religion with Allâh is Islâm. Those who were given the Scripture (Jews and Christians) did not differ except, out of mutual jealousy, after knowledge had come to them. And whoever disbelieves in the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, signs, revelations, etc.) of Allâh, then surely, Allâh is Swift in calling to account." />  <aya id="20" text="So if they dispute with you (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) say: &amp;quot;I have submitted myself to Allâh (in Islâm), and (so have) those who follow me.&amp;quot; And say to those who were given the Scripture (Jews and Christians) and to those who are illiterates (Arab pagans): &amp;quot;Do you (also) submit yourselves (to Allâh in Islâm)?&amp;quot; If they do, they are rightly guided; but if they turn away, your duty is only to convey the Message; and Allâh is All-Seer of (His ) slaves ." />  <aya id="21" text="Verily! Those who disbelieve in the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) of Allâh and kill the Prophets without right, and kill those men who order just dealings, &amp;#133; announce to them a painful torment." />  <aya id="22" text="They are those whose works will be lost in this world and in the Hereafter, and they will have no helpers." />  <aya id="23" text="Have you not seen those who have been given a portion of the Scripture? They are being invited to the Book of Allâh to settle their dispute, then a party of them turn away, and they are averse." />  <aya id="24" text="This is because they say: &amp;quot;The Fire shall not touch us but for a number of days.&amp;quot; And that which they used to invent regarding their religion has deceived them." />  <aya id="25" text="How (will it be) when We gather them together on the Day about which there is no doubt (i.e. the Day of Resurrection). And each person will be paid in full what he has earned? And they will not be dealt with unjustly." />  <aya id="26" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;O Allâh! Possessor of the kingdom, You give the kingdom to whom You will, and You take the kingdom from whom You will, and You endue with honour whom You will, and You humiliate whom You will. In Your Hand is the good. Verily, You are Able to do all things." />  <aya id="27" text="You make the night to enter into the day, and You make the day to enter into the night (i.e. increase and decrease in the hours of the night and the day during winter and summer), You bring the living out of the dead, and You bring the dead out of the living. And You give wealth and sustenance to whom You will, without limit (measure or account)." />  <aya id="28" text="Let not the believers take the disbelievers as &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ &lt;/I&gt;(supporters, helpers, etc.) instead of the believers, and whoever does that will never be helped by Allâh in any way, except if you indeed fear a danger from them. And Allâh warns you against Himself (His Punishment) , and to Allâh is the final return." />  <aya id="29" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Whether you hide what is in your breasts or reveal it, Allâh knows it, and He knows what is in the heavens and what is in the earth. And Allâh is Able to do all things.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="30" text="On the Day when every person will be confronted with all the good he has done, and all the evil he has done, he will wish that there were a great distance between him and his evil. And Allâh warns you against Himself (His Punishment) and Allâh is full of Kindness to the (His) slaves." />  <aya id="31" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; to mankind): &amp;quot;If you (really) love Allâh then follow me (i.e. accept Islâmic Monotheism, follow the Qur'ân and the &lt;I&gt;Sunnah&lt;/I&gt;), Allâh will love you and forgive you of your sins. And Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="32" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Obey Allâh and the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;).&amp;quot; But if they turn away, then Allâh does not like the disbelievers ." />  <aya id="33" text="Allâh chose Adam, Nûh (Noah), the family of Ibrâhim (Abraham) and the family of 'Imrân above the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind and jinns) (of their times)." />  <aya id="34" text="Offspring, one of the other, and Allâh is the All-Hearer, All-Knower." />  <aya id="35" text="(Remember) when the wife of 'Imrân said: &amp;quot;O my Lord! I have vowed to You what (the child that) is in my womb to be dedicated for Your services (free from all worldly work; to serve Your Place of worship), so accept this, from me. Verily, You are the All-Hearer, the All-Knowing.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="36" text="Then when she delivered her [child Maryam (Mary)], she said: &amp;quot;O my Lord! I have delivered a female child,&amp;quot; - and Allâh knew better what she delivered, - &amp;quot;And the male is not like the female, and I have named her Maryam (Mary), and I seek refuge with You (Allâh) for her and for her offspring from &lt;I&gt;Shaitan&lt;/I&gt; (Satan), the outcast.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="37" text="So her Lord (Allâh) accepted her with goodly acceptance. He made her grow in a good manner and put her under the care of Zakariyâ (Zachariya). Every time he entered &lt;I&gt;Al-Mihrâb&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;to (visit) her , he found her supplied with sustenance. He said: &amp;quot;O Maryam (Mary)! From where have you got this?&amp;quot; She said, &amp;quot;This is from Allâh.&amp;quot; Verily, Allâh provides sustenance to whom He wills, without limit.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="38" text="At that time Zakariyâ (Zachariya) invoked his Lord, saying: &amp;quot;O my Lord! Grant me from You, a good offspring. You are indeed the All-Hearer of invocation.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="39" text="Then the angels called him, while he was standing in prayer in &lt;I&gt;Al-Mihrâb &lt;/I&gt;(a praying place or a private room), (saying): &amp;quot;Allâh gives you glad tidings of Yahya (John), confirming (believing in) the Word from Allâh [i.e. the creation of 'Iesa (Jesus) &lt;&lt;code3&gt;&gt;&lt;&lt;codea&gt;&gt;, the Word from Allâh (&amp;quot;Be!&amp;quot; - and he was!)], noble, keeping away from sexual relations with women, a Prophet, from among the righteous.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="40" text="He said: &amp;quot;O my Lord! How can I have a son when I am very old, and my wife is barren?&amp;quot; Allâh said: &amp;quot;Thus Allâh does what He wills.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="41" text="He said: &amp;quot;O my Lord! Make a sign for me.&amp;quot; Allâh said: &amp;quot;Your sign is that you shall not speak to mankind for three days except with signals. And remember your Lord much (by praising Him again and again), and glorify (Him) in the afternoon and in the morning. &amp;quot;" />  <aya id="42" text="And (remember) when the angels said: &amp;quot;O Maryam (Mary)! Verily, Allâh has chosen you, purified you (from polytheism and disbelief), and chosen you above the women of the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind and jinns) (of her lifetime).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="43" text="O Mary! &amp;quot;Submit yourself with obedience to your Lord (Allâh, by worshipping none but Him Alone) and prostrate yourself, and &lt;I&gt;Irkâ'i &lt;/I&gt;(bow down etc.) along with &lt;I&gt;Ar-Râki'ûn &lt;/I&gt;(those who bow down etc.).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="44" text="This is a part of the news of the &lt;I&gt;Ghaib &lt;/I&gt;(unseen, i.e. the news of the past nations of which you have no knowledge) which We inspire you with (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;). You were not with them, when they cast lots with their pens as to which of them should be charged with the care of Maryam (Mary); nor were you with them when they disputed." />  <aya id="45" text="(Remember) when the angels said: &amp;quot;O Maryam (Mary)! Verily, Allâh gives you the glad tidings of a Word [&amp;quot;Be!&amp;quot; - and he was! i.e. 'Iesa (Jesus) the son of Maryam (Mary)] from Him, his name will be the Messiah 'Iesa (Jesus), the son of Maryam (Mary), held in honour in this world and in the Hereafter, and will be one of those who are near to Allâh.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="46" text="&amp;quot;He will speak to the people in the cradle and in manhood, and he will be one of the righteous.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="47" text="She said: &amp;quot;O my Lord! How shall I have a son when no man has touched me.&amp;quot; He said: &amp;quot;So (it will be) for Allâh creates what He wills. When He has decreed something, He says to it only: &amp;quot;Be!&amp;quot; and it is." />  <aya id="48" text="And He (Allâh) will teach him ['Iesa (Jesus)] the Book and &lt;I&gt;Al-Hikmah &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. the &lt;I&gt;Sunnah&lt;/I&gt;, the faultless speech of the Prophets, wisdom, etc.), (and) the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel)." />  <aya id="49" text="And will make him ['Iesa (Jesus)] a Messenger to the Children of Israel (saying): &amp;quot;I have come to you with a sign from your Lord, that I design for you out of clay, as it were, the figure of a bird, and breathe into it, and it becomes a bird by Allâh's Leave; and I heal him who was born blind, and the leper, and I bring the dead to life by Allâh's Leave. And I inform you of what you eat, and what you store in your houses. Surely, therein is a sign for you, if you believe." />  <aya id="50" text="And I have come confirming that which was before me of the Taurât (Torah), and to make lawful to you part of what was forbidden to you, and I have come to you with a proof from your Lord. So fear Allâh and obey me." />  <aya id="51" text="Truly! Allâh is my Lord and your Lord, so worship Him (Alone). This is the Straight Path." />  <aya id="52" text="Then when 'Iesa (Jesus) came to know of their disbelief, he said: &amp;quot;Who will be my helpers in Allâh's Cause?&amp;quot; &lt;I&gt;Al-Hawâriûn&lt;/I&gt; (the disciples) said: &amp;quot;We are the helpers of Allâh; we believe in Allâh, and bear witness that we are Muslims (i.e. we submit to Allâh).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="53" text="Our Lord! We believe in what You have sent down, and we follow the Messenger ['Iesa (Jesus)]; so write us down among those who bear witness (to the truth i.e. &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâha ill-Allâh &lt;/I&gt;- none has the right to be worshipped but Allâh)." />  <aya id="54" text="And they (disbelievers) plotted [to kill 'Iesa (Jesus) &lt;&lt;code3&gt;&gt;&lt;&lt;codea&gt;&gt;], and Allâh planned too. And Allâh is the Best of the planners." />  <aya id="55" text="And (remember) when Allâh said: &amp;quot;O 'Iesa (Jesus)! I will take you and raise you to Myself and clear you [of the forged statement that 'Iesa (Jesus) is Allâh's son] of those who disbelieve, and I will make those who follow you (Monotheists, who worship none but Allâh) superior to those who disbelieve [in the Oneness of Allâh, or disbelieve in some of His Messengers, e.g. Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;, 'Iesa (Jesus), Mûsa (Moses), etc., or in His Holy Books, e.g. the Taurât (Torah), the Injeel (Gospel), the Qur'ân] till the Day of Resurrection . Then you will return to Me and I will judge between you in the matters in which you used to dispute.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="56" text="&amp;quot;As to those who disbelieve, I will punish them with a severe torment in this world and in the Hereafter, and they will have no helpers.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="57" text="And as for those who believe (in the Oneness of Allâh) and do righteous good deeds, Allâh will pay them their reward in full. And Allâh does not like the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong-doers)." />  <aya id="58" text="This is what We recite to you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) of the Verses and the Wise Reminder (i.e. the Qur'ân)." />  <aya id="59" text="Verily, the likeness of 'Iesa (Jesus) before Allâh is the likeness of Adam. He created him from dust, then (He) said to him: &amp;quot;Be!&amp;quot; - and he was." />  <aya id="60" text="(This is) the truth from your Lord, so be not of those who doubt." />  <aya id="61" text="Then whoever disputes with you concerning him ['Iesa (Jesus)] after (all this) knowledge that has come to you, [i.e. 'Iesa (Jesus)] being a slave of Allâh, and having no share in Divinity) say: (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) &amp;quot;Come, let us call our sons and your sons, our women and your women, ourselves and yourselves - then we pray and invoke (sincerely) the Curse of Allâh upon those who lie.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="62" text="Verily! This is the true narrative [about the story of 'Iesa (Jesus)], and, &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâha ill-Allâh &lt;/I&gt;(none has the right to be worshipped but Allâh, the One and the Only True God, Who has neither a wife nor a son). And indeed, Allâh is the All-Mighty, the All-Wise." />  <aya id="63" text="And if they turn away (and do not accept these true proofs and evidences), then surely, Allâh is All-Aware of those who do mischief." />  <aya id="64" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians): Come to a word that is just between us and you, that we worship none but Allâh, and that we associate no partners with Him, and that none of us shall take others as lords besides Allâh . Then, if they turn away, say: &amp;quot;Bear witness that we are Muslims.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="65" text="O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Why do you dispute about Ibrâhim (Abraham), while the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel) were not revealed till after him? Have you then no sense?" />  <aya id="66" text="Verily, you are those who have disputed about that of which you have knowledge. Why do you then dispute concerning that which you have no knowledge? It is Allâh Who knows, and you know not." />  <aya id="67" text="Ibrâhim (Abraham) was neither a Jew nor a Christian, but he was a true Muslim &lt;I&gt;Hanifa &lt;/I&gt;(Islâmic Monotheism - to worship none but Allâh Alone) and he was not of &lt;I&gt;Al-Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(See V.2:105) ." />  <aya id="68" text="Verily, among mankind who have the best claim to Ibrâhim (Abraham) are those who followed him, and this Prophet (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and those who have believed (Muslims). And Allâh is the &lt;I&gt;Walî &lt;/I&gt;(Protector and Helper) of the believers." />  <aya id="69" text="A party of the people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians) wish to lead you astray. But they shall not lead astray anyone except themselves, and they perceive not." />  <aya id="70" text="O people of the Scripture! (Jews and Christians): &amp;quot;Why do you disbelieve in the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;of Allâh, [the Verses about Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; present in the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel)] while you (yourselves) bear witness (to their truth).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="71" text="O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians): &amp;quot;Why do you mix truth with falsehood and conceal the truth while you know?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="72" text="And a party of the people of the Scripture say: &amp;quot;Believe in the morning in that which is revealed to the believers (Muslims), and reject it at the end of the day, so that they may turn back." />  <aya id="73" text="And believe no one except the one who follows your religion. Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Verily! Right guidance is the Guidance of Allâh&amp;quot; and do not believe that anyone can receive like that which you have received (of Revelation) except when he follows your religion, otherwise they would engage you in argument before your Lord. Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;All the bounty is in the Hand of Allâh; He grants to whom He wills. And Allâh is All-Sufficient for His creatures' needs, the All-Knower.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="74" text="He selects for His Mercy (Islâm and the Qur'ân with Prophethood) whom He wills and Allâh is the Owner of Great Bounty." />  <aya id="75" text="Among the people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians) is he who, if entrusted with a &lt;I&gt;Cantar&lt;/I&gt; (a great amount of wealth, etc.), will readily pay it back; and among them there is he who, if entrusted with a single silver coin, will not repay it unless you constantly stand demanding, because they say: &amp;quot;There is no blame on us to betray and take the properties of the illiterates (Arabs).&amp;quot; But they tell a lie against Allâh while they know it." />  <aya id="76" text="Yes, whoever fulfils his pledge and fears Allâh much; verily, then Allâh loves those who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="77" text="Verily, those who purchase a small gain at the cost of Allâh's Covenant and their oaths, they shall have no portion in the Hereafter (Paradise). Neither will Allâh speak to them, nor look at them on the Day of Resurrection, nor will He purify them, and they shall have a painful torment." />  <aya id="78" text="And verily, among them is a party who distort the Book with their tongues (as they read), so that you may think it is from the Book, but it is not from the Book, and they say: &amp;quot;This is from Allâh,&amp;quot; but it is not from Allâh; and they speak a lie against Allâh while they know it." />  <aya id="79" text="It is not (possible) for any human being to whom Allâh has given the Book and &lt;I&gt;Al-Hukma &lt;/I&gt;(the knowledge and understanding of the laws of religion, etc.) and Prophethood to say to the people: &amp;quot;Be my worshippers rather than Allâh's.&amp;quot; On the contrary (he would say): &amp;quot;Be you &lt;I&gt;Rabbaniyun &lt;/I&gt;(learned men of religion who practise what they know and also preach others), because you are teaching the Book, and you are studying it.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="80" text="Nor would he order you to take angels and Prophets for lords (gods) Would he order you to disbelieve after you have submitted to Allâh's Will? (&lt;I&gt;Tafsir At-Tabarî&lt;/I&gt;)." />  <aya id="81" text="And (remember) when Allâh took the Covenant of the Prophets, saying: &amp;quot;Take whatever I gave you from the Book and &lt;I&gt;Hikmah &lt;/I&gt;(understanding of the Laws of Allâh, etc.), and afterwards there will come to you a Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) confirming what is with you; you must, then, believe in him and help him.&amp;quot; Allâh said: &amp;quot;Do you agree (to it) and will you take up My Covenant (which I conclude with you)?&amp;quot; They said: &amp;quot;We agree.&amp;quot; He said: &amp;quot;Then bear witness; and I am with you among the witnesses (for this).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="82" text="Then whoever turns away after this, they are the &lt;I&gt;Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(rebellious: those who turn away from Allâh's Obedience)." />  <aya id="83" text="Do they seek other than the religion of Allâh (the true Islâmic Monotheism worshipping none but Allâh Alone), while to Him submitted all creatures in the heavens and the earth, willingly or unwillingly. And to Him shall they all be returned." />  <aya id="84" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;We believe in Allâh and in what has been sent down to us, and what was sent down to Ibrâhim (Abraham), Ismâ'il (Ishmael), Ishâque (Isaac), Ya'qûb (Jacob) and &lt;I&gt;Al-Asbât &lt;/I&gt;[the twelve sons of Ya'qûb (Jacob)] and what was given to Mûsa (Moses), 'Iesa (Jesus) and the Prophets from their Lord. We make no distinction between one another among them and to Him (Allâh) we have submitted (in Islâm).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="85" text="And whoever seeks a religion other than Islâm, it will never be accepted of him, and in the Hereafter he will be one of the losers ." />  <aya id="86" text="How shall Allâh guide a people who disbelieved after their belief and after they bore witness that the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) is true and after clear proofs had come unto them? And Allâh guides not the people who are &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong-doers)." />  <aya id="87" text="They are those whose recompense is that on them (rests) the Curse of Allâh, of the angels, and of all mankind." />  <aya id="88" text="They will abide therein (Hell). Neither will their torment be lightened, nor will it be delayed or postponed (for a while)." />  <aya id="89" text="Except for those who repent after that and do righteous deeds. Verily, Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="90" text="Verily, those who disbelieved after their Belief and then went on increasing in their disbelief (i.e. disbelief in the Qur'ân and in Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) - never will their repentance be accepted [because they repent only by their tongues and not from their hearts]. And they are those who are astray." />  <aya id="91" text="Verily, those who disbelieved, and died while they were disbelievers, the (whole) earth full of gold will not be accepted from anyone of them even if they offered it as a ransom. For them is a painful torment and they will have no helpers." />  <aya id="92" text="By no means shall you attain &lt;I&gt;Al-Birr &lt;/I&gt;(piety, righteousness, etc., it means here Allâh's Reward, i.e. Paradise), unless you spend (in Allâh's Cause) of that which you love; and whatever of good you spend, Allâh knows it well." />  <aya id="93" text="All food was lawful to the Children of Israel, except what Israel made unlawful for himself before the Taurât (Torah) was revealed. Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Bring here the Taurât (Torah) and recite it, if you are truthful.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="94" text="Then after that, whosoever shall invent a lie against Allâh, &amp;#133; such shall indeed be the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(disbelievers)." />  <aya id="95" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Allâh has spoken the truth; follow the religion of Ibrâhim (Abraham) &lt;I&gt;Hanifa &lt;/I&gt;(Islâmic Monotheism, i.e. he used to worship Allâh Alone), and he was not of &lt;I&gt;Al-Mushrikûn&lt;/I&gt;.&amp;quot; (See V.2:105)" />  <aya id="96" text="Verily, the first House (of worship) appointed for mankind was that at &lt;I&gt;Bakkah &lt;/I&gt;(Makkah), full of blessing, and a guidance for &lt;I&gt;Al-'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(the mankind and jinns)." />  <aya id="97" text="In it are manifest signs (for example), the &lt;I&gt;Maqâm &lt;/I&gt;(place) of Ibrâhim (Abraham); whosoever enters it, he attains security. And &lt;I&gt;Hajj &lt;/I&gt;(pilgrimage to Makkah) to the House (Ka'bah) is a duty that mankind owes to Allâh, those who can afford the expenses (for one's conveyance, provision and residence); and whoever disbelieves [i.e. denies &lt;I&gt;Hajj &lt;/I&gt;(pilgrimage to Makkah), then he is a disbeliever of Allâh], then Allâh stands not in need of any of the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind and jinns) ." />  <aya id="98" text="Say: &amp;quot;O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Why do you reject the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;of Allâh (proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) while Allâh is Witness to what you do?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="99" text="Say: &amp;quot;O people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians)! Why do you stop those who have believed, from the Path of Allâh, seeking to make it seem crooked, while you (yourselves) are witnesses [to Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; as a Messenger of Allâh and Islâm (Allâh's Religion, i.e. to worship none but Him Alone)]? And Allâh is not unaware of what you do.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="100" text="O you who believe! If you obey a group of those who were given the Scripture (Jews and Christians), they would (indeed) render you disbelievers after you have believed!" />  <aya id="101" text="And how would you disbelieve, while unto you are recited the Verses of Allâh, and among you is His Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)? And whoever holds firmly to Allâh, (i.e. follows Islâm  Allâh's Religion, and obeys all that Allâh has ordered, practically), then he is indeed guided to a Right Path." />  <aya id="102" text="O you who believe! Fear Allâh (by doing all that He has ordered and by abstaining from all that He has forbidden) as He should be feared. [Obey Him, be thankful to Him, and remember Him always], and die not except in a state of Islâm (as Muslims) with complete submission to Allâh." />  <aya id="103" text="And hold fast, all of you together, to the Rope of Allâh (i.e. this Qur'ân), and be not divided among yourselves , and remember Allâh's Favour on you, for you were enemies one to another but He joined your hearts together, so that, by His Grace, you became brethren (in Islâmic Faith), and you were on the brink of a pit of Fire, and He saved you from it. Thus Allâh makes His &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.,) clear to you, that you may be guided." />  <aya id="104" text="Let there arise out of you a group of people inviting to all that is good (Islâm), enjoining &lt;I&gt;Al-Ma'rûf &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. Islâmic Monotheism and all that Islâm orders one to do) and forbidding &lt;I&gt;Al-Munkar &lt;/I&gt;(polytheism and disbelief and all that Islâm has forbidden). And it is they who are the successful." />  <aya id="105" text="And be not as those who divided and differed among themselves after the clear proofs had come to them. It is they for whom there is an awful torment." />  <aya id="106" text="On the Day (i.e. the Day of Resurrection) when some faces will become white and some faces will become black; as for those whose faces will become black (to them will be said): &amp;quot;Did you reject Faith after accepting it? Then taste the torment (in Hell) for rejecting Faith.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="107" text="And for those whose faces will become white, they will be in Allâh's Mercy (Paradise), therein they shall dwell forever." />  <aya id="108" text="These are the Verses of Allâh: We recite them to you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) in truth, and Allâh wills no injustice to the '&lt;I&gt;Alâmîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind and jinns)." />  <aya id="109" text="And to Allâh belongs all that is in the heavens and all that is in the earth. And all matters go back (for decision) to Allâh." />  <aya id="110" text="You [true believers in Islâmic Monotheism, and real followers of Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; and his &lt;I&gt;Sunnah &lt;/I&gt;(legal ways, etc.)] are the best of peoples ever raised up for mankind; you enjoin &lt;I&gt;Al-Ma'rûf &lt;/I&gt;(i.e. Islâmic Monotheism and all that Islâm has ordained) and forbid &lt;I&gt;Al-Munkar &lt;/I&gt;(polytheism, disbelief and all that Islâm has forbidden), and you believe in Allâh And had the people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians) believed, it would have been better for them; among them are some who have faith, but most of them are &lt;I&gt;Al-Fâsiqûn &lt;/I&gt;(disobedient to Allâh - and rebellious against Allâh's Command)." />  <aya id="111" text="They will do you no harm, barring a trifling annoyance; and if they fight against you, they will show you their backs, and they will not be helped." />  <aya id="112" text="Indignity is put over them wherever they may be, except when under a covenant (of protection) from Allâh, and from men; they have drawn on themselves the Wrath of Allâh, and destruction is put over them. This is because they disbelieved in the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) of Allâh and killed the Prophets without right. This is because they disobeyed (Allâh) and used to transgress beyond bounds (in Allâh's disobedience, crimes and sins)." />  <aya id="113" text="Not all of them are alike; a party of the people of the Scripture stand for the right, they recite the Verses of Allâh during the hours of the night, prostrating themselves in prayer." />  <aya id="114" text="They believe in Allâh and the Last Day; they enjoin &lt;I&gt;Al-Ma'rûf &lt;/I&gt;(Islâmic Monotheism, and following Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and forbid &lt;I&gt;Al-Munkar &lt;/I&gt;(polytheism, disbelief and opposing Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;); and they hasten in (all) good works; and they are among the righteous." />  <aya id="115" text="And whatever good they do, nothing will be rejected of them; for Allâh knows well those who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn&lt;/I&gt; (the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="116" text="Surely, those who reject Faith (disbelieve in Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; as being Allâh's Prophet and in all that which he has brought from Allâh), neither their properties, nor their offspring will avail them aught against Allâh. They are the dwellers of the Fire, therein they will abide . (&lt;I&gt;Tafsir At&amp;#173;Tabarî&lt;/I&gt;, Vol. 4, Page 58)." />  <aya id="117" text="The likeness of what they spend in this world is the likeness of a wind which is extremely cold; it struck the harvest of a people who did wrong aginst themselves and destroyed it, (i.e. the good deed of a person is only accepted if he is a monotheist and believes in all the Prophets of Allâh, including Christ &lt;&lt;code3&gt;&gt;&lt;&lt;codea&gt;&gt; and Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;). Allâh wronged them not, but they wronged themselves." />  <aya id="118" text="O you who believe! Take not as (your) &lt;I&gt;Bitânah &lt;/I&gt;(advisors, consultants, protectors, helpers, friends, etc.) those outside your religion (pagans, Jews, Christians, and hypocrites) since they will not fail to do their best to corrupt you. They desire to harm you severely. Hatred has already appeared from their mouths, but what their breasts conceal is far worse. Indeed We have made plain to you the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses) if you understand." />  <aya id="119" text="Lo! You are the ones who love them but they love you not, and you believe in all the Scriptures [i.e. you believe in the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel), while they disbelieve in your Book, the Qur'ân]. And when they meet you, they say, &amp;quot;We believe&amp;quot;. But when they are alone, they bite the tips of their fingers at you in rage. Say: &amp;quot;Perish in your rage. Certainly, Allâh knows what is in the breasts (all the secrets).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="120" text="If a good befalls you, it grieves them, but if some evil overtakes you, they rejoice at it. But if you remain patient and become &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn&lt;/I&gt; (the pious - see V.2:2), not the least harm will their cunning do to you. Surely, Allâh surrounds all that they do." />  <aya id="121" text="And (remember) when you (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) left your household in the morning to post the believers at their stations for the battle (of Uhud). And Allâh is All-Hearer, All-Knower." />  <aya id="122" text="When two parties from among you were about to lose heart, but Allâh was their &lt;I&gt;Walî &lt;/I&gt;(Supporter and Protector). And in Allâh should the believers put their trust." />  <aya id="123" text="And Allâh has already made you victorious at Badr, when you were a weak little force. So fear Allâh much [abstain from all kinds of sins and evil deeds which He has forbidden and love Allâh much, perform all kinds of good deeds which He has ordained] that you may be grateful." />  <aya id="124" text="(Remember) when you (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) said to the believers, &amp;quot;Is it not enough for you that your Lord (Allâh) should help you with three thousand angels; sent down?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="125" text="&amp;quot;Yes, if you hold on to patience and piety, and the enemy comes rushing at you; your Lord will help you with five thousand angels having marks (of distinction).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="126" text="Allâh made it not but as a message of good news for you and as an assurance to your hearts. And there is no victory except from Allâh, the All-Mighty, the All-Wise." />  <aya id="127" text="That He might cut off a part of those who disbelieve, or expose them to infamy, so that they retire frustrated." />  <aya id="128" text="Not for you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;, but for Allâh) is the decision; whether He turns in mercy to (pardons) them or punishes them; verily, they are the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists, disobedients, and wrong-doers, etc.)." />  <aya id="129" text="And to Allâh belongs all that is in the heavens and all that is in the earth. He forgives whom He wills, and punishes whom He wills. And Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="130" text="O you who believe! Eat not &lt;I&gt;Ribâ &lt;/I&gt;(usury) doubled and multiplied, but fear Allâh that you may be successful." />  <aya id="131" text="And fear the Fire, which is prepared for the disbelievers." />  <aya id="132" text="And obey Allâh and the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) that you may obtain mercy." />  <aya id="133" text="And march forth in the way (which leads to) forgiveness from your Lord, and for Paradise as wide as are the heavens and the earth, prepared for &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="134" text="Those who spend [in Allâh's Cause - deeds of charity, alms, etc.] in prosperity and in adversity, who repress anger, and who pardon men; verily, Allâh loves &lt;I&gt;Al-Muhsinûn&lt;/I&gt; &lt;I&gt; &lt;/I&gt;(the good&amp;#173;doers)." />  <aya id="135" text="And those who, when they have committed &lt;I&gt;Fahishah &lt;/I&gt;(illegal sexual intercourse etc.) or wronged themselves with evil, remember Allâh and ask forgiveness for their sins; - and none can forgive sins but Allâh - And do not persist in what (wrong) they have done, while they know." />  <aya id="136" text="For such, the reward is Forgiveness from their Lord, and Gardens with rivers flowing underneath (Paradise), wherein they shall abide forever. How excellent is this reward for the doers (who do righteous deeds according to Allâh's Orders)." />  <aya id="137" text="Many similar ways (and mishaps of life) were faced by nations (believers and disbelievers) that have passed away before you (as you have faced in the battle of Uhud), so travel through the earth, and see what was the end of those who disbelieved (in the Oneness of Allâh, and disobeyed Him and His Messengers)." />  <aya id="138" text="This (the Qur'ân) is a plain statement for mankind, a guidance and instruction to those who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2)." />  <aya id="139" text="So do not become weak (against your enemy), nor be sad, and you will be superior (in victory) if you are indeed (true) believers." />  <aya id="140" text="If a wound (and killing) has touched you, be sure a similar wound (and killing) has touched the others. And so are the days (good and not so good), We give to men by turns, that Allâh may test those who believe, and that He may take martyrs from among you. And Allâh likes not the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers)." />  <aya id="141" text="And that Allâh may test (or purify) the believers (from sins) and destroy the disbelievers." />  <aya id="142" text="Do you think that you will enter Paradise before Allâh tests those of you who fought (in His Cause) and (also) tests those who are &lt;I&gt;As-Sâbirin &lt;/I&gt;(the patient ones, etc.)?" />  <aya id="143" text="You did indeed wish for death (&lt;I&gt;Ash&amp;#173;Shahâdah &lt;/I&gt;- martyrdom) before you met it. Now you have seen it openly with your own eyes." />  <aya id="144" text="Muhammad (&lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) is no more than a Messenger, and indeed (many) Messengers have passed away before him. If he dies or is killed, will you then turn back on your heels (as disbelievers)? And he who turns back on his heels, not the least harm will he do to Allâh, and Allâh will give reward to those who are grateful." />  <aya id="145" text="And no person can ever die except by Allâh's Leave and at an appointed term. And whoever desires a reward in (this) world, We shall give him of it; and whoever desires a reward in the Hereafter, We shall give him thereof. And We shall reward the grateful." />  <aya id="146" text="And many a Prophet (i.e. many from amongst the Prophets) fought (in Allâh's Cause) and along with him (fought) large bands of religious learned men. But they never lost heart for that which did befall them in Allâh's Way, nor did they weaken nor degrade themselves. And Allâh loves &lt;I&gt;As-Sâbirin &lt;/I&gt;(the patient ones, etc.)." />  <aya id="147" text="And they said nothing but: &amp;quot;Our Lord! Forgive us our sins and our transgressions (in keeping our duties to You), establish our feet firmly, and give us victory over the disbelieving folk.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="148" text="So Allâh gave them the reward of this world, and the excellent reward of the Hereafter. And Allâh loves &lt;I&gt;Al-Muhsinûn &lt;/I&gt;(the good&amp;#173;doers - see the footnote of V.3:134)." />  <aya id="149" text="O you who believe! If you obey those who disbelieve, they will send you back on your heels, and you will turn back (from Faith) as losers." />  <aya id="150" text="Nay, Allâh is your &lt;I&gt;Maulâ &lt;/I&gt;(Patron, Lord, Helper and Protector, etc.), and He is the Best of helpers." />  <aya id="151" text="We shall cast terror into the hearts of those who disbelieve, because they joined others in worship with Allâh, for which He had sent no authority; their abode will be the Fire and how evil is the abode of the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers)." />  <aya id="152" text="And Allâh did indeed fulfil His Promise to you when you were killing them (your enemy) with His Permission; until (the moment) you lost your courage and fell to disputing about the order, and disobeyed after He showed you (of the booty) which you love. Among you are some that desire this world and some that desire the Hereafter. Then He made you flee from them (your enemy), that He might test you. But surely, He forgave you, and Allâh is Most Gracious to the believers." />  <aya id="153" text="(And remember) when you ran away (dreadfully) without even casting a side glance at anyone, and the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) was in your rear calling you back. There did Allâh give you one distress after another by way of requital to teach you not to grieve for that which had escaped you, nor for that which had befallen you. And Allâh is Well&amp;#173;Aware of all that you do." />  <aya id="154" text="Then after the distress, He sent down security for you. Slumber overtook a party of you, while another party was thinking about themselves (as how to save their ownselves, ignoring the others and the Prophet &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and thought wrongly of Allâh - the thought of ignorance. They said, &amp;quot;Have we any part in the affair?&amp;quot; Say you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Indeed the affair belongs wholly to Allâh.&amp;quot; They hide within themselves what they dare not reveal to you, saying: &amp;quot;If we had anything to do with the affair, none of us would have been killed here.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Even if you had remained in your homes, those for whom death was decreed would certainly have gone forth to the place of their death,&amp;quot; but that Allâh might test what is in your breasts; and to &lt;I&gt;Mahis&lt;/I&gt; that which was in your hearts (sins), and Allâh is All&amp;#173;Knower of what is in (your) breasts." />  <aya id="155" text="Those of you who turned back on the day the two hosts met (i.e. the battle of Uhud), it was &lt;I&gt;Shaitân&lt;/I&gt; (Satan) who caused them to backslide (run away from the battlefield) because of some (sins) they had earned. But Allâh, indeed, has forgiven them. Surely, Allâh is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Forbearing." />  <aya id="156" text="O you who believe! Be not like those who disbelieve (hypocrites) and who say to their brethren when they travel through the earth or go out to fight: &amp;quot;If they had stayed with us, they would not have died or been killed,&amp;quot; so that Allâh may make it a cause of regret in their hearts. It is Allâh that gives life and causes death. And Allâh is All&amp;#173;Seer of what you do." />  <aya id="157" text="And if you are killed or die in the Way of Allâh, forgiveness and mercy from Allâh are far better than all that they amass (of worldly wealths, etc.)." />  <aya id="158" text="And whether you die, or are killed, verily, unto Allâh you shall be gathered." />  <aya id="159" text="And by the Mercy of Allâh, you dealt with them gently. And had you been severe and harsh&amp;#173;hearted, they would have broken away from about you; so pass over (their faults), and ask (Allâh's) Forgiveness for them; and consult them in the affairs. Then when you have taken a decision, put your trust in Allâh, certainly, Allâh loves those who put their trust (in Him)." />  <aya id="160" text="If Allâh helps you, none can overcome you; and if He forsakes you, who is there after Him that can help you? And in Allâh (Alone) let believers put their trust." />  <aya id="161" text="It is not for any Prophet to take illegally a part of booty (&lt;I&gt;Ghulul&lt;/I&gt;) , and whosoever deceives his companions as regards the booty, he shall bring forth on the Day of Resurrection that which he took (illegally). Then every person shall be paid in full what he has earned, - and they shall not be dealt with unjustly." />  <aya id="162" text="Is then one who follows (seeks) the good Pleasure of Allâh (by not taking illegally a part of the booty) like the one who draws on himself the Wrath of Allâh (by taking a part of the booty illegally - &lt;I&gt;Ghulul&lt;/I&gt;)? - his abode is Hell, - and worst, indeed is that destination!" />  <aya id="163" text="They are in varying grades with Allâh, and Allâh is All&amp;#173;Seer of what they do." />  <aya id="164" text="Indeed Allâh conferred a great favour on the believers when He sent among them a Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)  from among themselves, reciting unto them His Verses (the Qur'ân), and purifying them (from sins by their following him), and instructing them (in) the Book (the Qur'ân) and &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Hikmah &lt;/I&gt;[the wisdom and the &lt;I&gt;Sunnah &lt;/I&gt;of the Prophet &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; (i.e. his legal ways, statements, acts of worship, etc.)], while before that they had been in manifest error." />  <aya id="165" text="(What is the matter with you?) When a single disaster smites you, although you smote (your enemies) with one twice as great, you say: &amp;quot;From where does this come to us?&amp;quot; Say (to them), &amp;quot;It is from yourselves (because of your evil deeds).&amp;quot; And Allâh has power over all things." />  <aya id="166" text="And what you suffered (of the disaster) on the day (of the battle of Uhud when) the two armies met, was by the leave of Allâh, in order that He might test the believers." />  <aya id="167" text="And that He might test the hypocrites, it was said to them: &amp;quot;Come, fight in the Way of Allâh or (at least) defend yourselves.&amp;quot; They said: &amp;quot;Had we known that fighting will take place, we would certainly have followed you.&amp;quot; They were that day, nearer to disbelief than to Faith, saying with their mouths what was not in their hearts. And Allâh has full knowledge of what they conceal." />  <aya id="168" text="(They are) the ones who said about their killed brethren while they themselves sat (at home): &amp;quot;If only they had listened to us, they would not have been killed.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Avert death from your ownselves, if you speak the truth.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="169" text="Think not of those who are killed in the Way of Allâh as dead. Nay, they are alive, with their Lord, and they have provision." />  <aya id="170" text="They rejoice in what Allâh has bestowed upon them of His Bounty, rejoicing for the sake of those who have not yet joined them, but are left behind (not yet martyred) that on them no fear shall come, nor shall they grieve." />  <aya id="171" text="They rejoice in a Grace and a Bounty from Allâh, and that Allâh will not waste the reward of the believers." />  <aya id="172" text="Those who answered (the Call of) Allâh and the Messenger (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) after being wounded; for those of them who did good deeds and feared Allâh, there is a great reward." />  <aya id="173" text="Those (i.e. believers) unto whom the people (hypocrites) said, &amp;quot;Verily, the people (pagans) have gathered against you (a great army), therefore, fear them.&amp;quot; But it (only) increased them in Faith, and they said: &amp;quot;Allâh (Alone) is Sufficient for us, and He is the Best Disposer of affairs (for us). &amp;quot;" />  <aya id="174" text="So they returned with Grace and Bounty from Allâh. No harm touched them; and they followed the good Pleasure of Allâh. And Allâh is the Owner of Great Bounty." />  <aya id="175" text="It is only &lt;I&gt;Shaitân&lt;/I&gt; (Satan) that suggests to you the fear of his &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;[supporters and friends (polytheists, disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh and in His Messenger, Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)], so fear them not, but fear Me, if you are (true) believers." />  <aya id="176" text="And let not those grieve you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) who rush with haste to disbelieve; verily, not the least harm will they do to Allâh. It is Allâh's Will to give them no portion in the Hereafter. For them there is a great torment." />  <aya id="177" text="Verily, those who purchase disbelief at the price of Faith, not the least harm will they do to Allâh. For them, there is a painful torment." />  <aya id="178" text="And let not the disbelievers think that Our postponing of their punishment is good for them. We postpone the punishment only so that they may increase in sinfulness. And for them is a disgracing torment." />  <aya id="179" text="Allâh will not leave the believers in the state in which you are now, until He distinguishes the wicked from the good. Nor will Allâh disclose to you the secrets of the &lt;I&gt;Ghaib &lt;/I&gt;(unseen), but Allâh chooses of His Messengers whom He pleases. So believe in Allâh and His Messengers. And if you believe and fear Allâh, then for you there is a great reward." />  <aya id="180" text="And let not those who covetously withhold of that which Allâh has bestowed on them of His Bounty (Wealth) think that it is good for them (and so they do not pay the obligatory &lt;I&gt;Zakât&lt;/I&gt;). Nay, it will be worse for them; the things which they covetously withheld shall be tied to their necks like a collar on the Day of Resurrection . And to Allâh belongs the heritage of the heavens and the earth; and Allâh is Well&amp;#173;Acquainted with all that you do." />  <aya id="181" text="Indeed, Allâh has heard the statement of those (Jews) who say: &amp;quot;Truly, Allâh is poor and we are rich!&amp;quot; We shall record what they have said and their killing of the Prophets unjustly, and We shall say: &amp;quot;Taste you the torment of the burning (Fire).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="182" text="This is because of that (evil) which your hands have sent before you. And certainly, Allâh is never unjust to (His) slaves." />  <aya id="183" text="Those (Jews) who said: &amp;quot;Verily, Allâh has taken our promise not to believe in any Messenger unless he brings to us an offering which the fire (from heaven) shall devour.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Verily, there came to you Messengers before me, with clear signs and even with what you speak of; why then did you kill them, if you are truthful?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="184" text="Then if they reject you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), so were Messengers rejected before you, who came with &lt;I&gt;Al-Baiyinât &lt;/I&gt;(clear signs, proofs, evidences) and the Scripture and the Book of Enlightenment." />  <aya id="185" text="Everyone shall taste death. And only on the Day of Resurrection shall you be paid your wages in full. And whoever is removed away from the Fire and admitted to Paradise, he indeed is successful. The life of this world is only the enjoyment of deception (a deceiving thing)." />  <aya id="186" text="You shall certainly be tried and tested in your wealth and properties and in your personal selves, and you shall certainly hear much that will grieve you from those who received the Scripture before you (Jews and Christians) and from those who ascribe partners to Allâh, but if you persevere patiently, and become &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2) then verily, that will be a determining factor in all affairs, and that is from the great matters, [which you must hold on with all your efforts]." />  <aya id="187" text="(And remember) when Allâh took a covenant from those who were given the Scripture (Jews and Christians) to make it (the news of the coming of Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; and the religious knowledge) known and clear to mankind, and not to hide it, but they threw it away behind their backs, and purchased with it some miserable gain! And indeed worst is that which they bought." />  <aya id="188" text="Think not that those who rejoice in what they have done (or brought about), and love to be praised for what they have not done,- think not you that they are rescued from the torment, and for them is a painful torment." />  <aya id="189" text="And to Allâh belongs the dominion of the heavens and the earth, and Allâh has power over all things." />  <aya id="190" text="Verily! In the creation of the heavens and the earth, and in the alternation of night and day, there are indeed signs for men of understanding." />  <aya id="191" text="Those who remember Allâh (always, and in prayers) standing, sitting, and lying down on their sides, and think deeply about the creation of the heavens and the earth, (saying): &amp;quot;Our Lord! You have not created (all) this without purpose, glory to You! (Exalted be You above all that they associate with You as partners). Give us salvation from the torment of the Fire." />  <aya id="192" text="&amp;quot;Our Lord! Verily, whom You admit to the Fire, indeed, You have disgraced him, and never will the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong-doers) find any helpers." />  <aya id="193" text="&amp;quot;Our Lord! Verily, we have heard the call of one (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) calling to Faith: 'Believe in your Lord,' and we have believed. Our Lord! Forgive us our sins and remit from us our evil deeds, and make us die in the state of righteousness along with &lt;I&gt;Al-Abrâr &lt;/I&gt;(those who are obedient to Allâh and follow strictly His Orders)." />  <aya id="194" text="&amp;quot;Our Lord! Grant us what You promised unto us through Your Messengers and disgrace us not on the Day of Resurrection, for You never break (Your) Promise.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="195" text="So their Lord accepted of them (their supplication and answered them), &amp;quot;Never will I allow to be lost the work of any of you, be he male or female. You are (members) one of another, so those who emigrated and were driven out from their homes, and suffered harm in My Cause, and who fought, and were killed (in My Cause), verily, I will remit from them their evil deeds and admit them into Gardens under which rivers flow (in Paradise); a reward from Allâh, and with Allâh is the best of rewards.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="196" text="Let not the free disposal (and affluence) of the disbelievers throughout the land deceive you." />  <aya id="197" text="A brief enjoyment; then, their ultimate abode is Hell; and worst indeed is that place for rest." />  <aya id="198" text="But, for those who fear their Lord, are Gardens under which rivers flow (in Paradise); therein are they to dwell (for ever), an entertainment from Allâh; and that which is with Allâh is the Best for &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Abrâr &lt;/I&gt;(those who are obedient to Allâh and follow strictly His Orders)." />  <aya id="199" text="And there are, certainly, among the people of the Scripture (Jews and Christians), those who believe in Allâh and in that which has been revealed to you, and in that which has been revealed to them, humbling themselves before Allâh. They do not sell the Verses of Allâh for a little price, for them is a reward with their Lord. Surely, Allâh is Swift in account." />  <aya id="200" text="O you who believe! Endure and be more patient (than your enemy), and guard your territory by stationing army units permanently at the places from where the enemy can attack you, and fear Allâh, so that you may be successful." /></sura>
