<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><sura id="66">  <aya id="1" text="O Prophet! Why do you ban (for yourself) that which Allâh has made lawful to you, seeking to please your wives? And Allâh is Oft-Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="2" text="Allâh has already ordained for you (O men), the dissolution of your oaths. And Allâh is your &lt;I&gt;Maula&lt;/I&gt; (Lord, or Master, or Protector, etc.) and He is the All-Knower, the All-Wise." />  <aya id="3" text="And (remember) when the Prophet (&lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) disclosed a matter in confidence to one of his wives (Hafsah), so when she told it (to another i.e. 'Aishah), and Allâh made it known to him, he informed part thereof and left a part. Then when he told her (Hafsah) thereof, she said: &amp;quot;Who told you this?&amp;quot; He said: &amp;quot;The All-Knower, the All-Aware (Allâh) has told me&amp;quot;." />  <aya id="4" text="If you two (wives of the Prophet &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;, namely 'Aishah and Hafsah ÑÖì &lt;&lt;code2&gt;&gt; &lt;&lt;codeb&gt;&gt;&lt;&lt;coded&gt;&gt;) turn in repentance to Allâh, (it will be better for you), your hearts are indeed so inclined (to oppose what the Prophet &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; likes), but if you help one another against him (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), then verily, Allâh is his &lt;I&gt;Maula&lt;/I&gt; (Lord, or Master, or Protector, etc.), and Jibrael (Gabriel), and the righteous among the believers, and furthermore, the angels are his helpers." />  <aya id="5" text="It may be if he divorced you (all) that his Lord will give him instead of you, wives better than you, Muslims (who submit to Allâh), believers, obedient to Allâh, turning to Allâh in repentance, worshipping Allâh sincerely, fasting or emigrants (for Allâh's sake), previously married and virgins." />  <aya id="6" text="O you who believe! Ward off from yourselves and your families a Fire (Hell) whose fuel is men and stones, over which are (appointed) angels stern (and) severe, who disobey not, (from executing) the Commands they receive from Allâh, but do that which they are commanded." />  <aya id="7" text="(It will be said in the Hereafter) O you who disbelieve (in the Oneness of Allâh - Islâmic Monotheism)! Make no excuses this Day! You are being requited only for what you used to do ." />  <aya id="8" text="O you who believe! Turn to Allâh with sincere repentance! It may be that your Lord will remit from you your sins, and admit you into Gardens under which rivers flow (Paradise) the Day that Allâh will not disgrace the Prophet (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and those who believe with him, their Light will run forward before them and with (their Records Books of deeds) in their right hands they will say: &amp;quot;Our Lord! Keep perfect our Light for us [and do not put it off till we cross over the &lt;I&gt;Sirât&lt;/I&gt; (a slippery bridge over the Hell) safely] and grant us forgiveness. Verily, You are Able to do all things .&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="9" text="O Prophet (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)! Strive hard against the disbelievers and the hypocrites, and be severe against them, their abode will be Hell, and worst indeed is that destination." />  <aya id="10" text="Allâh sets forth an example for those who disbelieve, the wife of Nûh (Noah) and the wife of Lout (Lot). They were under two of our righteous slaves, but they both betrayed their (husbands by rejecting their doctrine) so they [Nûh (Noah) and Lout (Lot) &lt;&lt;code3&gt;&gt;&lt;&lt;coded&gt;&gt; &lt;&lt;codea&gt;&gt;] benefited them (their respective wives) not, against Allâh, and it was said: &amp;quot;Enter the Fire along with those who enter!&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="11" text="And Allâh has set forth an example for those who believe, the wife of Fir'aun (Pharaoh), when she said: &amp;quot;My Lord! Build for me a home with You in Paradise, and save me from Fir'aun (Pharaoh) and his work, and save me from the people who are &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn&lt;/I&gt; (polytheists, wrong-doers and disbelievers in Allâh)." />  <aya id="12" text="And Maryam (Mary), the daughter of 'Imrân who guarded her chastity; and We breathed into (the sleeve of her shirt or her garment) through Our &lt;I&gt;Rûh&lt;/I&gt; [i.e. Jibrael (Gabriel) ], and she testified to the truth of the Words of her Lord [i.e. believed in the Words of Allâh: &amp;quot;Be!&amp;quot; and he was; that is 'Iesa (Jesus) &amp;#173; son of Maryam (Mary); as a Messenger of Allâh], and (also believed in) His Scriptures, and she was of the &lt;I&gt;Qanitîn&lt;/I&gt; (i.e. obedient to Allâh) ." /></sura>
