<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><sura id="6">  <aya id="1" text="All praises and thanks be to Allâh, Who (Alone) created the heavens and the earth, and originated the darkness and the light, yet those who disbelieve hold others as equal with their Lord." />  <aya id="2" text="He it is Who has created you from clay, and then has decreed a stated term (for you to die). And there is with Him another determined term (for you to be resurrected), yet you doubt (in the Resurrection)." />  <aya id="3" text="And He is Allâh (to be worshipped Alone) in the heavens and on the earth, He knows what you conceal and what you reveal, and He knows what you earn (good or bad)." />  <aya id="4" text="And never an &lt;I&gt;Ayah &lt;/I&gt;(sign) comes to them from the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) of their Lord, but that they have been turning away from it." />  <aya id="5" text="Indeed, they rejected the truth (the Qur'ân and Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) when it came to them, but there will come to them the news of that (the torment) which they used to mock at." />  <aya id="6" text="Have they not seen how many a generation before them We have destroyed whom We had established on the earth such as We have not established you? And We poured out on them rain from the sky in abundance, and made the rivers flow under them. Yet We destroyed them for their sins, and created after them other generations." />  <aya id="7" text="And even if We had sent down unto you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) a Message written on paper so that they could touch it with their hands, the disbelievers would have said: &amp;quot;This is nothing but obvious magic!&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="8" text="And they say: &amp;quot;Why has not an angel been sent down to him?&amp;quot; Had We sent down an angel, the matter would have been judged at once, and no respite would be granted to them." />  <aya id="9" text="And had We appointed him an angel, We indeed would have made him a man, and We would have certainly caused them confusion in a matter which they have already covered with confusion (i.e. the Message of Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)." />  <aya id="10" text="And indeed (many) Messengers were mocked before you, but their scoffers were surrounded by the very thing that they used to mock at." />  <aya id="11" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Travel in the land and see what was the end of those who rejected truth.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="12" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;To whom belongs all that is in the heavens and the earth?&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;To Allâh. He has prescribed Mercy for Himself . Indeed He will gather you together on the Day of Resurrection, about which there is no doubt. Those who destroy themselves will not believe [in Allâh as being the only &lt;I&gt;Ilâh &lt;/I&gt;(God), and Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; as being one of His Messengers, and in Resurrection, etc.]." />  <aya id="13" text="And to Him belongs whatsoever exists in the night and the day, and He is the All&amp;#173;Hearing, the All&amp;#173;Knowing.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="14" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Shall I take as a &lt;I&gt;Walî &lt;/I&gt;(helper, protector, etc.) any other than Allâh, the Creator of the heavens and the earth? And it is He Who feeds but is not fed.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Verily, I am commanded to be the first of those who submit themselves to Allâh (as Muslims).&amp;quot; And be not you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) of the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;[polytheists, pagans, idolaters and disbelievers in the Oneness of Allâh]." />  <aya id="15" text="Say: &amp;quot;I fear, if I disobey my Lord, the torment of a Mighty Day.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="16" text="Who is averted from (such a torment) on that Day, (Allâh) has surely been Merciful to him. And that would be the obvious success." />  <aya id="17" text="And if Allâh touches you with harm, none can remove it but He, and if He touches you with good, then He is Able to do all things." />  <aya id="18" text="And He is the Irresistible, above His slaves, and He is the All-Wise, Well&amp;#173;Acquainted with all things." />  <aya id="19" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;What thing is the most great in witness?&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Allâh (the Most Great!) is Witness between me and you; this Qur'ân has been revealed to me that I may therewith warn you and whomsoever it may reach. Can you verily bear witness that besides Allâh there are other &lt;I&gt;alihâ &lt;/I&gt;(gods)?&amp;quot; Say &amp;quot;I bear no (such) witness!&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;But in truth He (Allâh) is the only one &lt;I&gt;Ilâh &lt;/I&gt;(God). And truly I am innocent of what you join in worship with Him.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="20" text="Those to whom We have given the Scripture (Jews and Christians) recognize him (i.e. Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; as a Messenger of Allâh, and they also know that there is no &lt;I&gt;Ilah &lt;/I&gt;(God) but Allâh and Islâm is Allâh's Religion), as they recognize their own sons. Those who destroy themselves will not believe . (&lt;I&gt;Tafsir At-Tabarî&lt;/I&gt;)" />  <aya id="21" text="And who does more wrong than he who invents a lie against Allâh or rejects His &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, revelations, etc.)? Verily, the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers, etc.) shall never be successful." />  <aya id="22" text="And on the Day when We shall gather them all together, We shall say to those who joined partners in worship (with Us): &amp;quot;Where are your partners (false deities) whom you used to assert (as partners in worship with Allâh)?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="23" text="There will then be (left) no &lt;I&gt;Fitnah&lt;/I&gt; (excuses or statements or arguments) for them but to say: &amp;quot;By Allâh, our Lord, we were not those who joined others in worship with Allâh.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="24" text="Look! How they lie against themselves! But the (lie) which they invented will disappear from them." />  <aya id="25" text="And of them there are some who listen to you; but We have set veils on their hearts, so they understand it not, and deafness in their ears; if they see every one of the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) they will not believe therein; to the point that when they come to you to argue with you, the disbelievers say: &amp;quot;These are nothing but tales of the men of old.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="26" text="And they prevent others from him (from following Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) and they themselves keep away from him, and (by doing so) they destroy not but their ownselves, yet they perceive (it) not." />  <aya id="27" text="If you could but see when they will be held over the (Hell) Fire! They will say: &amp;quot;Would that we were but sent back (to the world)! Then we would not deny the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, revelations, etc.) of our Lord, and we would be of the believers!&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="28" text="Nay, it has become manifest to them what they had been concealing before. But if they were returned (to the world), they would certainly revert to that which they were forbidden. And indeed they are liars." />  <aya id="29" text="And they said: &amp;quot;There is no (other life) but our (present) life of this world, and never shall we be resurrected (on the Day of Resurrection).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="30" text="If you could but see when they will be held (brought and made to stand) in front of their Lord! He will say: &amp;quot;Is not this (Resurrection and the taking of the accounts) the truth?&amp;quot; They will say: &amp;quot;Yes, by our Lord!&amp;quot; He will then say: &amp;quot;So taste you the torment because you used not to believe.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="31" text="They indeed are losers who denied their Meeting with Allâh , until all of a sudden, the Hour (signs of death) is on them, and they say: &amp;quot;Alas for us that we gave no thought to it,&amp;quot; while they will bear their burdens on their backs; and evil indeed are the burdens that they will bear!" />  <aya id="32" text="And the life of this world is nothing but play and amusement. But far better is the house in the Hereafter for those who are &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2). Will you not then understand?" />  <aya id="33" text="We know indeed the grief which their words cause you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): it is not you that they deny, but it is the Verses (the Qur'ân) of Allâh that the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers) deny." />  <aya id="34" text="Verily, (many) Messengers were denied before you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), but with patience they bore the denial, and they were hurt, till Our Help reached them, and none can alter the Words (Decisions) of Allâh. Surely there has reached you the information (news) about the Messengers (before you)." />  <aya id="35" text="If their aversion (from you, O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt; and from that with which you have been sent) is hard on you, (and you cannot be patient from their harm to you), then if you were able to seek a tunnel in the ground or a ladder to the sky, so that you may bring them a sign (and you cannot do it, so be patient). And had Allâh willed, He could have gathered them together (all) unto true guidance, so be not you one of those who are &lt;I&gt;Al-Jâhilûn &lt;/I&gt;(the ignorant)." />  <aya id="36" text="It is only those who listen (to the Message of Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), will respond (benefit from it), but as for the dead (disbelievers), Allâh will raise them up, then to Him they will be returned (for their recompense)." />  <aya id="37" text="And they said: &amp;quot;Why is not a sign sent down to him from his Lord?&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Allâh is certainly Able to send down a sign, but most of them know not.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="38" text="There is not a moving (living) creature on earth, nor a bird that flies with its two wings, but are communities like you. We have neglected nothing in the Book, then unto their Lord they (all) shall be gathered." />  <aya id="39" text="Those who reject Our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) are deaf and dumb in darkness. Allâh sends astray whom He wills and He guides on the Straight Path whom He wills." />  <aya id="40" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Tell me if Allâh's Torment comes upon you, or the Hour comes upon you, would you then call upon any one other than Allâh? (Reply) if you are truthful!&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="41" text="Nay! To Him Alone you call, and, if He will, He would remove that (distress) for which you call upon Him, and you forget at that time whatever partners you joined with Him (in worship)!" />  <aya id="42" text="Verily, We sent (Messengers) to many nations before you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;). And We seized them with extreme poverty (or loss in wealth) and loss in health with calamities so that they might believe with humility." />  <aya id="43" text="When Our Torment reached them, why then did they not believe with humility? But their hearts became hardened, and &lt;I&gt;Shaitân &lt;/I&gt;(Satan) made fair&amp;#173;seeming to them that which they used to do." />  <aya id="44" text="So, when they forgot (the warning) with which they had been reminded, We opened to them the gates of every (pleasant) thing, until in the midst of their enjoyment in that which they were given, all of a sudden, We took them to punishment, and lo! They were plunged into destruction with deep regrets and sorrows." />  <aya id="45" text="So the roots of the people who did wrong were cut off. And all the praises and thanks be to Allâh, the Lord of the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind, jinns, and all that exists)." />  <aya id="46" text="Say (to the disbelievers): &amp;quot;Tell me, if Allâh took away your hearing and your sight, and sealed up your hearts, who is there - an &lt;I&gt;ilâh &lt;/I&gt;(a god) other than Allâh who could restore them to you?&amp;quot; See how variously We explain the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.), yet they turn aside." />  <aya id="47" text="Say: &amp;quot;Tell me, if the punishment of Allâh comes to you suddenly (during the night), or openly (during the day), will any be destroyed except the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong-doing people)?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="48" text="And We send not the Messengers but as givers of glad tidings and as warners. So whosoever believes and does righteous good deeds, upon such shall come no fear, nor shall they grieve." />  <aya id="49" text="But those who reject Our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.), the torment will touch them for their disbelief (and for their belying the Message of Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;). [&lt;I&gt;Tafsir Al-Qurtubî&lt;/I&gt;]." />  <aya id="50" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;I don't tell you that with me are the treasures of Allâh, nor (that) I know the unseen; nor I tell you that I am an angel. I but follow what is revealed to me by inspiration.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Are the blind and the one who sees equal? will you not then take thought?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="51" text="And warn therewith (the Qur'ân) those who fear that they will be gathered before their Lord, when there will be neither a protector nor an intercessor for them besides Him, so that they may fear Allâh and keep their duty to Him (by abstaining from committing sins and by doing all kinds of good deeds which He has ordained)." />  <aya id="52" text="And turn not away those who invoke their Lord, morning and afternoon seeking His Face. You are accountable for them in nothing, and they are accountable for you in nothing, that you may turn them away, and thus become of the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(unjust)." />  <aya id="53" text="Thus We have tried some of them with others, that they might say: &amp;quot;Is it these (poor believers) that Allâh has favoured from amongst us?&amp;quot; Does not Allâh know best those who are grateful?" />  <aya id="54" text="When those who believe in Our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) come to you, say: &lt;I&gt;&amp;quot;Salâmun 'Alaikum&amp;quot; &lt;/I&gt;(peace be on you); your Lord has written Mercy for Himself, so that, if any of you does evil in ignorance, and thereafter repents and does righteous good deeds (by obeying Allâh), then surely, He is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Merciful." />  <aya id="55" text="And thus do We explain the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) in detail, that the way of the &lt;I&gt;Mujrimûn &lt;/I&gt;(criminals, polytheists, sinners), may become manifest." />  <aya id="56" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;I have been forbidden to worship those whom you invoke (worship) besides Allâh.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;I will not follow your vain desires. If I did, I would go astray, and I would not be one of the rightly guided.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="57" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;I am on clear proof from my Lord (Islâmic Monotheism), but you deny (the truth that has come to me from Allâh). I have not gotten what you are asking for impatiently (the torment). The decision is only for Allâh, He declares the truth, and He is the Best of judges.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="58" text="Say: &amp;quot;If I had that which you are asking for impatiently (the torment), the matter would have been settled at once between me and you, but Allâh knows best the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers, etc.).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="59" text="And with Him are the keys of the &lt;I&gt;Ghaib &lt;/I&gt;(all that is hidden), none knows them but He. And He knows whatever there is in (or on) the earth and in the sea; not a leaf falls, but he knows it. There is not a grain in the darkness of the earth nor anything fresh or dry, but is written in a Clear Record." />  <aya id="60" text="It is He, Who takes your souls by night (when you are asleep), and has knowledge of all that you have done by day, then he raises (wakes) you up again that a term appointed (your life period) be fulfilled, then in the end unto Him will be your return. Then He will inform you what you used to do." />  <aya id="61" text="He is the Irresistible, Supreme over His slaves, and He sends guardians (angels guarding and writing all of one's good and bad deeds) over you , until when death approaches one of you, Our Messengers (angel of death and his assistants) take his soul, and they never neglect their duty." />  <aya id="62" text="Then they are returned to Allâh, their &lt;I&gt;Maulâ &lt;/I&gt;[True Master (God), the Just Lord (to reward them)]. Surely, His is the judgement and He is the Swiftest in taking account." />  <aya id="63" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Who rescues you from the darkness of the land and the sea (dangers like storms), when you call upon Him in humility and in secret (saying): If He (Allâh) only saves us from this (danger), we shall truly be grateful.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="64" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Allâh rescues you from it and from all (other) distresses, and yet you worship others besides Allâh.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="65" text="Say: &amp;quot;He has power to send torment on you from above or from under your feet, or to cover you with confusion in party strife, and make you to taste the violence of one another.&amp;quot; See how variously We explain the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.), so that they may understand." />  <aya id="66" text="But your people (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) have denied it (the Qur'ân) though it is the truth. Say: &amp;quot;I am not responsible for your affairs.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="67" text="For every news there is a fact, i.e. for everything there is an appointed term (and it is also said that for every deed there is a recompense) and you will come to know." />  <aya id="68" text="And when you (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) see those who engage in a false conversation about Our Verses (of the Qur'ân) by mocking at them, stay away from them till they turn to another topic. And if &lt;I&gt;Shaitân&lt;/I&gt; (Satan) causes you to forget, then after the remembrance sit not you in the company of those people who are the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers, etc.)." />  <aya id="69" text="Those who fear Allâh, keep their duty to Him and avoid evil are not responsible for them (the disbelievers) in any case, but (their duty) is to remind them, that they may avoid that (mockery at the Qur'ân). [The order of this Verse was cancelled (abrogated) by the Verse 4:140]." />  <aya id="70" text="And leave alone those who take their religion as play and amusement, and are deceived by the life of this world. But remind (them) with it (the Qur'ân) lest a person be given up to destruction for that which he has earned, when he will find for himself no protector or intercessor besides Allâh, and even if he offers every ransom, it will not be accepted from him. Such are they who are given up to destruction because of that which they have earned. For them will be a drink of boiling water and a painful torment because they used to disbelieve." />  <aya id="71" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Shall we invoke others besides Allâh (false deities), that can do us neither good nor harm, and shall we turn on our heels after Allâh has guided us (to true Monotheism)? - like one whom the &lt;I&gt;Shayâtin &lt;/I&gt;(devils) have made to go astray, confused (wandering) through the earth, his companions calling him to guidance (saying): 'Come to us.' &amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Verily, Allâh's Guidance is the only guidance, and we have been commanded to submit (ourselves) to the Lord of the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind, jinns and all that exists);" />  <aya id="72" text="And to perform &lt;I&gt;As-Salât&lt;/I&gt; (&lt;I&gt;Iqâmat-as-Salât&lt;/I&gt;)&amp;quot;, and to be obedient to Allâh and fear Him, and it is He to Whom you shall be gathered." />  <aya id="73" text="It is He Who has created the heavens and the earth in truth, and on the Day (i.e. the Day of Resurrection) He will say: &amp;quot;Be!&amp;quot;, - and it shall become. His Word is the truth. His will be the dominion on the Day when the trumpet will be blown. All&amp;#173;Knower of the unseen and the seen. He is the All&amp;#173;Wise, Well-Aware (of all things)." />  <aya id="74" text="And (remember) when Ibrâhim (Abraham) said to his father Azar: &amp;quot;Do you take idols as &lt;I&gt;âlihâ &lt;/I&gt;(gods)? Verily, I see you and your people in manifest error. &amp;quot;" />  <aya id="75" text="Thus did we show Ibrâhim (Abraham) the kingdom of the heavens and the earth that he be one of those who have Faith with certainty." />  <aya id="76" text="When the night covered him over with darkness he saw a star. He said: &amp;quot;This is my lord.&amp;quot; But when it set, he said: &amp;quot;I like not those that set.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="77" text="When he saw the moon rising up, he said: &amp;quot;This is my lord.&amp;quot; But when it set, he said: &amp;quot;Unless my Lord guides me, I shall surely be among the erring people.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="78" text="When he saw the sun rising up, he said: &amp;quot;This is my lord. This is greater.&amp;quot; But when it set, he said: &amp;quot;O my people! I am indeed free from all that you join as partners in worship with Allâh." />  <aya id="79" text="Verily, I have turned my face towards Him Who has created the heavens and the earth &lt;I&gt;Hanifa &lt;/I&gt;(Islâmic Monotheism, i.e. worshipping none but Allâh Alone) and I am not of &lt;I&gt;Al-Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(see V.2:105)&amp;quot;." />  <aya id="80" text="His people disputed with him. He said: &amp;quot;Do you dispute with me concerning Allâh while He has guided me, and I fear not those whom you associate with Allâh in worship. (Nothing can happen to me) except when my Lord (Allâh) wills something. My Lord comprehends in His Knowledge all things. Will you not then remember?" />  <aya id="81" text="And how should I fear those whom you associate in worship with Allâh (though they can neither benefit nor harm), while you fear not that you have joined in worship with Allâh things for which He has not sent down to you any authority. (So) which of the two parties has more right to be in security? If you but know.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="82" text="It is those who believe (in the Oneness of Allâh and worship none but Him Alone) and confuse not their belief with &lt;I&gt;Zulm&lt;/I&gt; (wrong i.e. by worshipping others besides Allâh), for them (only) there is security and they are the guided." />  <aya id="83" text="And that was Our Proof which We gave Ibrâhim (Abraham) against his people. We raise whom We will in degrees. Certainly your Lord is All&amp;#173;Wise, All&amp;#173;Knowing." />  <aya id="84" text="And We bestowed upon him Ishâque (Isaac) and Ya'qûb (Jacob), each of them We guided, and before him, We guided Nûh (Noah), and among his progeny Dawûd (David), Sulaimân (Solomon), Ayub (Job), Yûsuf (Joseph), Mûsa (Moses), and Hârûn (Aaron). Thus do We reward the good&amp;#173;doers." />  <aya id="85" text="And Zakariyâ (Zachariya), and Yahya (John) and 'Iesa (Jesus) and Iliyâs (Elias), each one of them was of the righteous." />  <aya id="86" text="And Ismâ'il (Ishmael) and Al-Yas'â (Elisha), and Yûnus (Jonah) and Lout (Lot), and each one of them We preferred above the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind and jinns) (of their times)." />  <aya id="87" text="And also some of their fathers and their progeny and their brethren, We chose them, and We guided them to a Straight Path." />  <aya id="88" text="This is the Guidance of Allâh with which He guides whomsoever He will of His slaves. But if they had joined in worship others with Allâh, all that they used to do would have been of no benefit to them." />  <aya id="89" text="They are those whom We gave the Book, &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Hukm &lt;/I&gt;(understanding of the religious laws), and Prophethood. But if these disbelieve therein (the Book, &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Hukm &lt;/I&gt;and Prophethood), then, indeed We have entrusted it to a people (such as the Companions of Prophet Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) who are not disbelievers therein." />  <aya id="90" text="They are those whom Allâh had guided. So follow their guidance. Say: &amp;quot;No reward I ask of you for this (the Qur'ân). It is only a reminder for the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind and jinns).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="91" text="They (the Jews, Quraish pagans, idolaters, etc.) did not estimate Allâh with an estimation due to Him when they said: &amp;quot;Nothing did Allâh send down to any human being (by inspiration).&amp;quot; Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Who then sent down the Book which Mûsa (Moses) brought, a light and a guidance to mankind which you (the Jews) have made into (separate) papersheets, disclosing (some of it) and concealing (much). And you (believers in Allâh and His Messenger Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;), were taught (through the Qur'ân) that which neither you nor your fathers knew.&amp;quot; Say: &amp;quot;Allâh (sent it down).&amp;quot; Then leave them to play in their vain discussions. (&lt;I&gt;Tafsir Al-Qurtubî,&lt;/I&gt; Vol.7, Page 37)." />  <aya id="92" text="And this (the Qur'ân) is a blessed Book which We have sent down, confirming (the revelations) which came before it, so that you may warn the Mother of Towns (i.e. Makkah) and all those around it. Those who believe in the Hereafter believe in (the Qur'ân), and they are constant in guarding their &lt;I&gt;Salât &lt;/I&gt;(prayers)." />  <aya id="93" text="And who can be more unjust than he who invents a lie against Allâh, or says: &amp;quot;I have received inspiration,&amp;quot; whereas he is not inspired in anything; and who says, &amp;quot;I will reveal the like of what Allâh has revealed.&amp;quot; And if you could but see when the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers, etc.) are in the agonies of death, while the angels are stretching forth their hands (saying): &amp;quot;Deliver your souls! This day you shall be recompensed with the torment of degradation because of what you used to utter against Allâh other than the truth. And you used to reject His &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) with disrespect! &amp;quot;" />  <aya id="94" text="And truly you have come unto Us alone (without wealth, companions or anything else) as We created you the first time. You have left behind you all that which We had bestowed on you. We see not with you your intercessors whom you claimed to be partners with Allâh. Now all relations between you and them have been cut off, and all that you used to claim has vanished from you." />  <aya id="95" text="Verily! It is Allâh Who causes the seed&amp;#173;grain and the fruit&amp;#173;stone (like date&amp;#173;stone, etc.) to split and sprout. He brings forth the living from the dead, and it is He Who brings forth the dead from the living. Such is Allâh, then how are you deluded away from the truth?" />  <aya id="96" text="(He is the) Cleaver of the daybreak. He has appointed the night for resting, and the sun and the moon for reckoning. Such is the measuring of the All&amp;#173;Mighty, the All&amp;#173;Knowing." />  <aya id="97" text="It is He Who has set the stars for you, so that you may guide your course with their help through the darkness of the land and the sea. We have (indeed) explained in detail Our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, Revelations, etc.) for people who know." />  <aya id="98" text="It is He Who has created you from a single person (Adam), and has given you a place of residing (on the earth or in your mother's wombs) and a place of storage [in the earth (in your graves) or in your father's loins]. Indeed, We have explained in detail Our revelations (this Qur'ân) for people who understand." />  <aya id="99" text="It is He Who sends down water (rain) from the sky, and with it We bring forth vegetation of all kinds, and out of it We bring forth green stalks, from which We bring forth thick clustered grain. And out of the date&amp;#173;palm and its spathe come forth clusters of dates hanging low and near, and gardens of grapes, olives and pomegranates, each similar (in kind) yet different (in variety and taste). Look at their fruits when they begin to bear, and the ripeness thereof. Verily! In these things there are signs for people who believe." />  <aya id="100" text="Yet, they join the jinns as partners in worship with Allâh, though He has created them (the jinns), and they attribute falsely without knowledge sons and daughters to Him. Be He Glorified and Exalted above (all) that they attribute to Him." />  <aya id="101" text="He is the Originator of the heavens and the earth. How can He have children when He has no wife? He created all things and He is the All-Knower of everything ." />  <aya id="102" text="Such is Allâh, your Lord! &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâha illa Huwa &lt;/I&gt;(none has the right to be worshipped but He), the Creator of all things. So worship Him (Alone), and He is the &lt;I&gt;Wakîl &lt;/I&gt;(Trustee, Disposer of affairs, Guardian, etc.) over all things." />  <aya id="103" text="No vision can grasp Him, but His Grasp is over all vision. He is the Most Subtle and Courteous, Well&amp;#173;Acquainted with all things." />  <aya id="104" text="Verily, proofs have come to you from your Lord, so whosoever sees, will do so for (the good of) his ownself, and whosoever blinds himself, will do so to his own harm, and I (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) am not a watcher over you." />  <aya id="105" text="Thus We explain variously the Verses so that they (the disbelievers) may say: &amp;quot;You have studied (the Books of the people of the Scripture and brought this Qur'ân from that)&amp;quot; and that We may make the matter clear for the people who have knowledge." />  <aya id="106" text="Follow what has been inspired to you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) from your Lord, &lt;I&gt;Lâ ilâha illa Huwa &lt;/I&gt;(none has the right to be worshipped but He) and turn aside from &lt;I&gt;Al-Mushrikûn&lt;/I&gt;." />  <aya id="107" text="Had Allâh willed, they would not have taken others besides Him in worship. And We have not made you a watcher over them nor are you set over them to dispose of their affairs." />  <aya id="108" text="And insult not those whom they (disbelievers) worship besides Allâh, lest they insult Allâh wrongfully without knowledge. Thus We have made fair&amp;#173;seeming to each people its own doings; then to their Lord is their return and He shall then inform them of all that they used to do." />  <aya id="109" text="And they swear their strongest oaths by Allâh, that if there came to them a sign, they would surely believe therein. Say: &amp;quot;Signs are but with Allâh and what will make you (Muslims) perceive that (even) if it (the sign) came, they will not believe?&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="110" text="And We shall turn their hearts and their eyes away (from guidance), as they refused to believe therein for the first time, and We shall leave them in their trespass to wander blindly." />  <aya id="111" text="And even if We had sent down unto them angels, and the dead had spoken unto them, and We had gathered together all things before their very eyes, they would not have believed, unless Allâh willed, but most of them behave ignorantly." />  <aya id="112" text="And so We have appointed for every Prophet enemies - &lt;I&gt;Shayâtin&lt;/I&gt; (devils) among mankind and jinns, inspiring one another with adorned speech as a delusion (or by way of deception). If your Lord had so willed, they would not have done it, so leave them alone with their fabrications. (&lt;I&gt;Tafseer Qurtubi,&lt;/I&gt; Vol.7, Page 67)" />  <aya id="113" text="(And this is in order) that the hearts of those who disbelieve in the Hereafter may incline to such (deceit), and that they may remain pleased with it, and that they may commit what they are committing (all kinds of sins and evil deeds, etc.)." />  <aya id="114" text="[Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;)] &amp;quot;Shall I seek a judge other than Allâh while it is He Who has sent down unto you the Book (The Qur'ân), explained in detail.&amp;quot; Those unto whom We gave the Scripture [the Taurât (Torah) and the Injeel (Gospel)] know that it is revealed from your Lord in truth. So be not you of those who doubt." />  <aya id="115" text="And the Word of your Lord has been fulfilled in truth and in justice. None can change His Words. And He is the All&amp;#173;Hearer, the All&amp;#173;Knower." />  <aya id="116" text="And if you obey most of those on earth, they will mislead you far away from Allâh's Path. They follow nothing but conjectures, and they do nothing but lie." />  <aya id="117" text="Verily, your Lord! It is He Who knows best who strays from His Way, and He knows best the rightly guided ones." />  <aya id="118" text="So eat of that (meat) on which Allâh's Name has been pronounced (while slaughtering the animal), if you are believers in His &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.)." />  <aya id="119" text="And why should you not eat of that (meat) on which Allâh's Name has been pronounced (at the time of slaughtering the animal), while He has explained to you in detail what is forbidden to you, except under compulsion of necessity? And surely many do lead (mankind) astray by their own desires through lack of knowledge. Certainly your Lord knows best the transgressors." />  <aya id="120" text="Leave (O mankind, all kinds of) sin, open and secret. Verily, those who commit sin will get due recompense for that which they used to commit." />  <aya id="121" text="Eat not (O believers) of that (meat) on which Allâh's Name has not been pronounced (at the time of the slaughtering of the animal), for sure it is &lt;I&gt;Fisq &lt;/I&gt;(a sin and disobedience of Allâh). And certainly, the &lt;I&gt;Shayâtin&lt;/I&gt; (devils) do inspire their friends (from mankind) to dispute with you, and if you obey them [by making &lt;I&gt;Al&amp;#173;Maytatah &lt;/I&gt;(a dead animal) legal by eating it], then you would indeed be &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists) [because they (devils and their friends) made lawful to you to eat that which Allâh has made unlawful to eat and you obeyed them by considering it lawful to eat, and by doing so you worshipped them, and to worship others besides Allâh is polytheism]." />  <aya id="122" text="Is he who was dead (without Faith by ignorance and disbelief) and We gave him life (by knowledge and Faith) and set for him a light (of Belief) whereby he can walk amongst men, like him who is in the darkness (of disbelief, polytheism and hypocrisy) from which he can never come out? Thus it is made fair&amp;#173;seeming to the disbelievers that which they used to do." />  <aya id="123" text="And thus We have set up in every town great ones of its wicked people to plot therein. But they plot not except against their ownselves, and they perceive (it) not." />  <aya id="124" text="And when there comes to them a sign (from Allâh) they say: &amp;quot;We shall not believe until we receive the like of that which the Messengers of Allâh had received.&amp;quot; Allâh knows best with whom to place His Message. Humiliation and disgrace from Allâh and a severe torment will overtake the criminals (polytheists, sinners, etc.) for that which they used to plot." />  <aya id="125" text="And whomsoever Allâh wills to guide, He opens his breast to Islâm, and whomsoever He wills to send astray, He makes his breast closed and constricted, as if he is climbing up to the sky. Thus Allâh puts the wrath on those who believe not." />  <aya id="126" text="And this is the Path of your Lord (the Qur'ân and Islâm) leading Straight. We have detailed Our Revelations for a people who take heed." />  <aya id="127" text="For them will be the home of peace (Paradise) with their Lord. And He will be their &lt;I&gt;Walî &lt;/I&gt;(Helper and Protector) because of what they used to do." />  <aya id="128" text="And on the Day when He will gather them (all) together (and say): &amp;quot;O you assembly of jinns! Many did you mislead of men,&amp;quot; and their &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ&lt;/I&gt;' (friends and helpers, etc.) amongst men will say: &amp;quot;Our Lord! We benefited one from the other, but now we have reached our appointed term which You did appoint for us.&amp;quot; He will say: &amp;quot;The Fire be your dwelling&amp;#173;place, you will dwell therein forever, except as Allâh may will. Certainly your Lord is All&amp;#173;Wise, All&amp;#173;Knowing.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="129" text="And thus We do make the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers, etc.) &lt;I&gt;Auliyâ' &lt;/I&gt;(supporters and helpers) one to another (in committing crimes etc.), because of that which they used to earn." />  <aya id="130" text="O you assembly of jinns and mankind! &amp;quot;Did not there come to you Messengers from amongst you, reciting unto you My Verses and warning you of the meeting of this Day of yours?&amp;quot; They will say: &amp;quot;We bear witness against ourselves.&amp;quot; It was the life of this world that deceived them. And they will bear witness against themselves that they were disbelievers." />  <aya id="131" text="This is because your Lord would not destroy the (populations of) towns for their wrong&amp;#173;doing (i.e. associating others in worship along with Allâh) while their people were unaware (so the Messengers were sent)." />  <aya id="132" text="For all there will be degrees (or ranks) according to what they did. And your Lord is not unaware of what they do." />  <aya id="133" text="And your Lord is Rich (Free of all wants), full of Mercy, if He will, He can destroy you, and in your place make whom He will as your successors, as He raised you from the seed of other people." />  <aya id="134" text="Surely, that which you are promised will verily come to pass, and you cannot escape (from the Punishment of Allâh)." />  <aya id="135" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;O my people! Work according to your way, surely, I too am working (in my way), and you will come to know for which of us will be the (happy) end in the Hereafter. Certainly the &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers, etc.) will not be successful.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="136" text="And they assign to Allâh a share of the tilth and cattle which He has created, and they say: &amp;quot;This is for Allâh according to their pretending, and this is for our (Allâh's so&amp;#173;called) partners.&amp;quot; But the share of their (Allâh's so&amp;#173;called) &amp;quot;partners&amp;quot; reaches not Allâh, while the share of Allâh reaches their (Allâh's so&amp;#173;called) &amp;quot;partners&amp;quot;! Evil is the way they judge!" />  <aya id="137" text="And so to many of the &lt;I&gt;Mushrikûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists - see V.2:105) their (Allâh's so&amp;#173;called) &amp;quot;partners&amp;quot; have made fair-seeming the killing of their children, in order to lead them to their own destruction and cause confusion in their religion. And if Allâh had willed they would not have done so. So leave them alone with their fabrications." />  <aya id="138" text="And according to their pretending, they say that such and such cattle and crops are forbidden, and none should eat of them except those whom we allow. And (they say) there are cattle forbidden to be used for burden or any other work, and cattle on which (at slaughtering) the Name of Allâh is not pronounced; lying against Him (Allâh). He will recompense them for what they used to fabricate." />  <aya id="139" text="And they say: &amp;quot;What is in the bellies of such and such cattle (milk or foetus) is for our males alone, and forbidden to our females (girls and women), but if it is born dead, then all have shares therein.&amp;quot; He will punish them for their attribution (of such false orders to Allâh). Verily, He is All&amp;#173;Wise, All&amp;#173;Knower. (&lt;I&gt;Tafsir At&amp;#173;Tabarî,&lt;/I&gt; Vol. 8, Page 49)." />  <aya id="140" text="Indeed lost are they who have killed their children, from folly, without knowledge, and have forbidden that which Allâh has provided for them, inventing a lie against Allâh. They have indeed gone astray and were not guided." />  <aya id="141" text="And it is He Who produces gardens trellised and untrellised, and date&amp;#173;palms, and crops of different shape and taste (its fruits and its seeds) and olives, and pomegranates, similar (in kind) and different (in taste). Eat of their fruit when they ripen, but pay the due thereof (its &lt;I&gt;Zakât, &lt;/I&gt;according to Allâh's Orders 1/10th or 1/20th) on the day of its harvest, and waste not by extravagance . Verily, He likes not &lt;I&gt;Al-Musrifûn &lt;/I&gt;(those who waste by extravagance)," />  <aya id="142" text="And of the cattle (are some) for burden (like camels etc.) and (some are) small (unable to carry burden like sheep, goats etc. for food, meat, milk, wool etc.). Eat of what Allâh has provided for you, and follow not the footsteps of &lt;I&gt;Shaitân&lt;/I&gt; (Satan). Surely he is to you an open enemy." />  <aya id="143" text="Eight pairs; of the sheep two (male and female) , and of the goats two (male and female). Say: &amp;quot;Has He forbidden the two males or the two females, or (the young) which the wombs of the two females enclose? Inform me with knowledge if you are truthful.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="144" text="And of the camels two (male and female), and of oxen two (male and female). Say: &amp;quot;Has He forbidden the two males or the two females or (the young) which the wombs of the two females enclose? Or were you present when Allâh ordered you such a thing? Then who does more wrong than one who invents a lie against Allâh, to lead mankind astray without knowledge. Certainly Allâh guides not the people who are &lt;I&gt;Zâlimûn &lt;/I&gt;(polytheists and wrong&amp;#173;doers, etc.).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="145" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;I find not in that which has been inspired to me anything forbidden to be eaten by one who wishes to eat it, unless it be &lt;I&gt;Maytatah &lt;/I&gt;(a dead animal) or blood poured forth (by slaughtering or the like), or the flesh of swine (pork, etc.) for that surely is impure, or impious (unlawful) meat (of an animal) which is slaughtered as a sacrifice for others than Allâh (or has been slaughtered for idols, etc., or on which Allâh's Name has not been mentioned while slaughtering). But whosoever is forced by necessity without wilful disobedience, nor transgressing due limits, (for him) certainly, your Lord is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Merciful.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="146" text="And unto those who are Jews, We forbade every (animal) with undivided hoof, and We forbade them the fat of the ox and the sheep except what adheres to their backs or their entrails, or is mixed up with a bone. Thus We recompensed them for their rebellion [committing crimes like murdering the Prophets, eating of &lt;I&gt;Ribâ &lt;/I&gt;(usury), etc.]. And verily, We are Truthful." />  <aya id="147" text="If they (Jews) belie you (Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) say you: &amp;quot;Your Lord is the Owner of Vast Mercy, and never will His Wrath be turned back from the people who are &lt;I&gt;Mujrimûn &lt;/I&gt;(criminals, polytheists, sinners, etc.).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="148" text="Those who took partners (in worship) with Allâh will say: &amp;quot;If Allâh had willed, we would not have taken partners (in worship) with Him, nor would our fathers, and we would not have forbidden anything (against His Will).&amp;quot; Likewise belied those who were before them, (they argued falsely with Allâh's Messengers), till they tasted of Our Wrath. Say: &amp;quot;Have you any knowledge (proof) that you can produce before us? Verily, you follow nothing but guess and you do nothing but lie.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="149" text="Say: &amp;quot;With Allâh is the perfect proof and argument, (i.e. the Oneness of Allâh, the sending of His Messengers and His Holy Books, etc. to mankind), had He so willed, He would indeed have guided you all.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="150" text="Say: &amp;quot;Bring forward your witnesses, who can testify that Allâh has forbidden this. Then if they testify, testify not you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) with them. And you should not follow the vain desires of such as treat Our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) as falsehoods, and such as believe not in the Hereafter, and they hold others as equal (in worship) with their Lord.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="151" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Come, I will recite what your Lord has prohibited you from: Join not anything in worship with Him; be good and dutiful to your parents; kill not your children because of poverty - We provide sustenance for you and for them; come not near to &lt;I&gt;Al-Fawâhish &lt;/I&gt;(shameful sins, illegal sexual intercourse, etc.) whether committed openly or secretly, and kill not anyone whom Allâh has forbidden, except for a just cause (according to Islâmic law). This He has commanded you that you may understand." />  <aya id="152" text="&amp;quot;And come not near to the orphan's property, except to improve it, until he (or she) attains the age of full strength; and give full measure and full weight with justice. We burden not any person, but that which he can bear. And whenever you give your word (i.e. judge between men or give evidence, etc.), say the truth even if a near relative is concerned, and fulfill the Covenant of Allâh, This He commands you, that you may remember." />  <aya id="153" text="&amp;quot;And verily, this (i.e. Allâh's Commandments mentioned in the above two Verses 151 and 152) is my Straight Path, so follow it, and follow not (other) paths, for they will separate you away from His Path. This He has ordained for you that you may become &lt;I&gt;Al-Muttaqûn &lt;/I&gt;(the pious - see V.2:2).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="154" text="Then, We gave Mûsa (Moses) the Book [the Taurât (Torah)], to complete (Our Favour) upon those who would do right, and explaining all things in detail and a guidance and a mercy that they might believe in the meeting with their Lord." />  <aya id="155" text="And this is a blessed Book (the Qur'ân) which We have sent down, so follow it and fear Allâh (i.e. do not disobey His Orders), that you may receive mercy (i.e. saved from the torment of Hell)." />  <aya id="156" text="Lest you (pagan Arabs) should say: &amp;quot;The Book was only sent down to two sects before us (the Jews and the Christians), and for our part, we were in fact unaware of what they studied.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="157" text="Or lest you (pagan Arabs) should say: &amp;quot;If only the Book had been sent down to us, we would surely have been better guided than they (Jews and Christians).&amp;quot; So now has come unto you a clear proof (the Qur'ân) from your Lord, and a guidance and a mercy. Who then does more wrong than one who rejects the &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;(proofs, evidences, verses, lessons, signs, revelations, etc.) of Allâh and turns away therefrom? We shall requite those who turn away from Our &lt;I&gt;Ayât &lt;/I&gt;with an evil torment, because of their turning away (from them). [&lt;I&gt;Tafsir At-Tabari, &lt;/I&gt;Vol. 8, Page 95]" />  <aya id="158" text="Do they then wait for anything other than that the angels should come to them, or that your Lord should come, or that some of the Signs of your Lord should come (i.e. portents of the Hour e.g., arising of the sun from the west)! The day that some of the Signs of your Lord do come, no good will it do to a person to believe then, if he believed not before, nor earned good (by performing deeds of righteousness) through his Faith. Say: &amp;quot;Wait you! we (too) are waiting.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="159" text="Verily, those who divide their religion and break up into sects (all kinds of religious sects) , you (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) have no concern in them in the least. Their affair is only with Allâh, Who then will tell them what they used to do." />  <aya id="160" text="Whoever brings a good deed (Islâmic Monotheism and deeds of obedience to Allâh and His Messenger &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) shall have ten times the like thereof to his credit, and whoever brings an evil deed (polytheism, disbelief, hypocrisy, and deeds of disobedience to Allâh and His Messenger &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;) shall have only the recompense of the like thereof, and they will not be wronged." />  <aya id="161" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Truly, my Lord has guided me to a Straight Path, a right religion, the religion of Ibrâhim (Abraham), &lt;I&gt;Hanifa &lt;/I&gt;[i.e. the true Islâmic Monotheism - to believe in One God (Allâh i.e. to worship none but Allâh, Alone)] and he was not of &lt;I&gt;Al-Mushrikûn&lt;/I&gt; (see V.2:105).&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="162" text="Say (O Muhammad &lt;tt&gt;SAW&lt;/tt&gt;): &amp;quot;Verily, my &lt;I&gt;Salât&lt;/I&gt; (prayer), my sacrifice, my living, and my dying are for Allâh, the Lord of the &lt;I&gt;'Alamîn &lt;/I&gt;(mankind, jinns and all that exists)." />  <aya id="163" text="&amp;quot;He has no partner. And of this I have been commanded, and I am the first of the Muslims.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="164" text="Say: &amp;quot;Shall I seek a lord other than Allâh, while He is the Lord of all things? No person earns any (sin) except against himself (only), and no bearer of burdens shall bear the burden of another. Then unto your Lord is your return, so He will tell you that wherein you have been differing.&amp;quot;" />  <aya id="165" text="And it is He Who has made you generations coming after generations, replacing each other on the earth. And He has raised you in ranks, some above others that He may try you in that which He has bestowed on you. Surely your Lord is Swift in retribution, and certainly He is Oft&amp;#173;Forgiving, Most Merciful." /></sura>
